<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A key to the Kings cabinet; or Animadversions upon the three printed speeches, of Mr Lisle, Mr Tate, and Mr Browne, spoken at a common-hall in London, 3. July, 1645. Detecting the malice and falshood of their blasphemous observations made upon the King and Queenes letters.</title>
            <author>Browne, Thomas, 1604?-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5181A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E297_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E297[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A key to the Kings cabinet; or Animadversions upon the three printed speeches, of Mr Lisle, Mr Tate, and Mr Browne, spoken at a common-hall in London, 3. July, 1645. Detecting the malice and falshood of their blasphemous observations made upon the King and Queenes letters.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, 1604?-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the University,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Browne.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Lisle, John, et al.  Three speeches spoken at a common-hall.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lisle, John, ca. 1610-1664. --  Three speeches spoken at a common-hall --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tate, Zouch, 1605 or 6-1650 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Browne, John, ca. 1581-1659 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> KEY TO THE KINGS CABINET; OR ANIMADVERSIONS upon the three Printed Speeches, of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Liſle,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tate,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Browne,</hi> ſpoken at a Common Hall in <hi>London, 3. July,</hi> 1645. Detecting the Malice and Falſhood of their Blaſphemous Obſervations made upon the KING and QVEENES LETTERS.</p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD, Printer to the Univerſity, 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113157:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113157:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Key to the King's Cabinet,</hi> OR Certaine Animadverſions upon the Three Printed Speeches of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Liſle,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tate,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Browne,</hi> ſpoken at a Common-Hall in <hi>London, 3. July,</hi> 1645.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the <hi>Athenians</hi> waged Warre againſt <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> amongſt many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall advantages of the dice, which Fortune caſt upon them, They chanced one day to intercept a Packet of the King's Letters, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Helladius Beſantin.</note> on the way; which, with great Triumph and Oſtentation, They preſently ſent unto their great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell at <hi>Athens,</hi> there to be opened, in a <hi>Full Houſe,</hi> before them: nothing doubting, but that, beſides the <hi>Credit</hi> of the ſurprize, this <hi>profit</hi> alſo would redound unto them, That thoſe Letters of <hi>Philip's</hi> would informe them ſomething for their advantage; would open to them ſomething of his Deſigne in the managery and carrying on of that preſent Warre, which could not but have good influence upon their owne Affaires, which were then in hot diſpute and agitation. When the whole <hi>Houſe</hi> was ſet, and the Packet opened; There were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſundry Letters found, ſaith our <hi>Author,</hi> and to ſundry Perſons of Note and Truſt at Court, addreſſed: but none of them were any thing conſiderable in their Contents, in reſpect of any light which they gave, or umbrage of diſcovery which they made, concerning either <hi>Philips</hi> Actions or Councells.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113157:3"/> At laſt, they found one Letter amongſt the reſt, with this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription, <hi>Philippus Olympiadi.</hi> That is, <hi>Philip</hi> to <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias.</hi> And that Letter was a Letter from the King to his owne <hi>deare Wife;</hi> to <hi>Olympias</hi> the Queene. And in that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, had <hi>Philip</hi> opened unto her the very ſecrets of his Heart. In that Letter, beſides many warme teſtimonies of his entire Conjugall Faith, and Innocent Affection, had <hi>Philip</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto her, the whole frame and faſhion of all his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. In that Letter had he laid open before her, the ſad hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of his ſufferings, from thoſe unquiet <hi>Athenians,</hi> that would never let him reſt; and of thoſe hopefull expedients alſo, which preſented themſelves in the ſhape of Comfort to him, whereby he doubted not in ſhort time to worke himſelfe out of His Vexations and Troubles. Yet, notwithſtanding all this, ſaith the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> when the ſeale of that Letter was even now breaking up, as the others had been broken up before it; when <hi>Philip's</hi> whole Deſigne was now upon the inſtant of diſcovery, and lay at the mercy of that Enemies Hand, againſt whoſe onely Head it was contrived and framed; The whole Aſſembly roſe in ſome diſorder: cryed out, that, that Letter ſhould by no meanes be opened; but underſtanding that it was addreſſed to <hi>Olympias</hi> the Queene, without any the leaſt violation offered to the Sacred Seale, to <hi>Her</hi> they ſent it: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that it was a <hi>barbarous</hi> and <hi>unmanly</hi> thing, to betray the ſecrets between <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> unto the whole World, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the knowledge thereof would prove never ſo benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and advantageous unto them that did it. <hi>Adeò vtile, non anteponebant honeſto</hi> (for ſo <hi>Helladius</hi> concludes) So did theſe Turbulent <hi>Athenians</hi> yet, preferre their <hi>Honeſty</hi> before their <hi>Profit;</hi> and as great as their <hi>Hoſtility</hi> was, yet, their <hi>Humanity</hi> ſtill, was greater.</p>
            <p>Without queſtion, if the Rebels of this Age, could but <hi>doe</hi> halfe ſo well like <hi>Men,</hi> as they can <hi>ſay,</hi> like <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> They would never have embas'd their late Victory with ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Trophees, as they have done. They would never have lead a poore <hi>Cabinet,</hi> Captive; and diſplayed the King and Queenes <hi>Letters</hi> in triumph, as they did, their <hi>Colours;</hi> They
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113157:3"/> would never have made the Spoyles of very <hi>Manhood,</hi> a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the wanton ſpleen of <hi>Man.</hi> They would never have <hi>commanded</hi> their Oratours to lay downe that vomit at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> which they had lickt up, at <hi>Westminſter.</hi> They would never have proſtituted thoſe chaſt and holy Papers, to the baſe adulteries of all common Eyes; They would never have ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated and chaw'd thoſe Letters into <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> that the People might more eaſily <hi>conceive</hi> them: When I have good reaſon to thinke, that there are not <hi>Three</hi> men in both the <hi>two</hi> Houſes, that were ever yet honeſt enough, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>underſtand</hi> them. But the <hi>Tree of knowledge,</hi> doth ſtill find the luck in moſt men to be deſired, before the <hi>Tree of Life;</hi> And, ſo factious and ſeditious Perſons, can get any <hi>fewell</hi> to maintaine Rebellion but in the credit of a <hi>flame:</hi> they care not whether they ranſack <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> to fetch it. They care not, whether they break downe the <hi>Hedges</hi> of Nations, or of Nature (for ſo they call the <hi>Lawes</hi>) if but either of them will afford a few crackling thornes, or any combuſtible matter whatſoever, that will foment and feed it.</p>
            <p>Men indeed, whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> will allow them to ranſack <hi>God's</hi> Cabinet, no marvaile, if they quickly find <hi>reaſon</hi> not to ſpare the <hi>King's.</hi> The greateſt complaint is, They are not <hi>Aequall</hi> Villaines; they are not <hi>Indifferent,</hi> no, not in their very <hi>Riots.</hi> They doe not uſe both Parties <hi>alike.</hi> For, what Papers ſoever which they find in <hi>God's</hi> Cabinet, although they breath nothing but the ſevere and ſoure expreſſions of <hi>Hate,</hi> and of <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> and that deſtruction to be extended to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of all <hi>Mankind,</hi> yet if they publiſh thoſe Papers, they doe it, ſtill, in the way of <hi>Service</hi> to God, and for his <hi>Glory.</hi> But what Papers ſoever, which they light on in the <hi>King's</hi> Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, although they breath nothing but the ſweets of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Preſervation,</hi> and that preſervation to be contracted up to his owne Juſt <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Right;</hi> nay, to his owne very <hi>Life:</hi> yet, They will be ſure to publiſh them in the way of the greateſt <hi>Diſſervice</hi> which they can imagine, and to his moſt <hi>Diſhonour.</hi> They will not let him <hi>loath</hi> a Rebel, nay, they will not let him <hi>love</hi> a Wife; They will not let him uſe his <hi>Sword,</hi> nay,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113157:4"/> they will not let him uſe his <hi>Pen,</hi> but they will expoſe him for it. Like thoſe ill natur'd Enemies to <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, whom <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks of, who when they had no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt him, upon the ſuddain, for which they might revile him: at laſt exclaymed upon him, for ſcratching of his head, with one finger, leaſt they ſhould have had nothing, to have ſaid againſt him.</p>
            <p>And truly, that which is the reſult of all their <hi>Obſervations</hi> and <hi>Annotations,</hi> and <hi>Speeches,</hi> with which they ſpatter and aſperſe the King, is little more: So very little, that I ſhould never have thought all which hath been objected, worth an Anſwer, but, that I ſuſpect ſome men have arrived to ſuch a ſingularity of folly, as, to take that for an <hi>Honour,</hi> which is meant for a <hi>Neglect;</hi> but that, I believe, there are ſome men, of ſuch an all-ſufficient pride; that, if they ſay a thing, never ſo fooliſh and ridiculous, and receive no preſent <hi>Anſwer</hi> to that which they have ſaid; They make that advantage of their get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> no <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which <hi>Cato,</hi> they ſay, made, when he could get no <hi>Statue;</hi> who gave out, that it was more for his Honour and Reputation, that poſterity ſhould enquire, why <hi>Cato</hi> had <hi>no</hi> Statue, then why he <hi>had.</hi> And therefore I ſhall take them, all three in order as they lye; beginning firſt with M. <hi>Liſles</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, whoſe maſculine eloquence it ſeems, was thought worthieſt to enjoy the Mayden-head of the Citties Attention, who beſpeaks them in the manner following.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M. <hi>Liſle</hi> his Speech.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord</hi> Major, <hi>and you worthy Gentlemen of the Famous Citty of</hi> London, <hi>I am commanded, by the Lords and Commons in</hi> Parliament <hi>Aſſembled, to obſerve to you ſome paſſages, out of theſe</hi> Letters <hi>which you have heard; They are paſſages of that nature, though it be moſt happy to this Kingdom and Parliament to know them, yet my very heart doth bleed to report them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Well <hi>ſaid,</hi> good <hi>obedient</hi> Oratour <hi>Higgin:</hi> you have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, it ſeems, but what you were <hi>commanded;</hi> But, I ſay not,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113157:4"/> well <hi>done</hi> my Lord <hi>Major,</hi> and you worthy Gentlemen of the famous City of <hi>London;</hi> for, you have done a thing which no body could <hi>command</hi> you; you have reſigned and given up your ſences and your underſtanding here, to three <hi>Brothers of the Obſervance;</hi> as if you were able to marke nothing of your ſelves, but what they <hi>Obſerve</hi> unto you. What my Maſters? are the <hi>Walloones</hi> that came over lately, crept already from the <hi>Campe</hi> into your <hi>Councell,</hi> that a Common-Hall at <hi>London</hi> cannot underſtand <hi>Engliſh</hi> when they heare it? Have you not only loſt your <hi>Loyalty,</hi> but your very <hi>Language,</hi> that you muſt have an Interpreter to your own Mothers tongue? take my word for it, the Letters, although they were not the old Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh foretoppe in their forehead, of, <hi>After my hearty commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations remembred unto you, hoping to God that you are in good health, as I am at the writing hereof,</hi> yet, they are writ in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but errand <hi>Engliſh;</hi> The King and the Queen, as much as you ſuſpect them for ſuperſtition, are not yet come to that height of Popery, as to write their mutuall private Letters, in an <hi>unknown Tongue.</hi> For ſhame then, be not ſuch Wittalls to your own underſtanding, as to ſay, you know not Engliſh when you doe? I can tell you, the <hi>Coſt</hi> of this Interpreter, may chance prove greater then the <hi>Worſhip;</hi> you ſee, M. <hi>Liſles</hi> heart <hi>bleeds</hi> in the very begining of the buſineſſe; It was never known but, <hi>Bloud</hi> would have <hi>Bloud,</hi> you know; and I feare, your <hi>Hearts</hi> alſo, (that is your Purſes) will <hi>bleed,</hi> before ever it be done. There is ſo much of the <hi>Phariſee</hi> between you, that if his <hi>Trumpet</hi> ſhould goe before, and your <hi>Almes</hi> ſhould not follow after; I would ſweare one of you were very much out, in playing of his part: but M. <hi>Liſle</hi> is not out; for he goes on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt thing that I ſhall obſerve to you, is concerning the King's endeavours to bring Forraigne Forces, a Forraigne Prince with an Army into this Kingdom: By His Letters to the Queen, which you have heard read, He endeavours to basten the Duke of</hi> Loraine <hi>with an Army into</hi> England. <hi>It is well known to the Parliament, that the Duke of</hi> Loraine, <hi>is a Prince highly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113157:5"/> eſteem'd at</hi> Rome; <hi>the moſt complying with Ieſuites, of any Prince in Chriſtendomes and yet the King writes to the Queen, to haſten the Duke of</hi> Loraine <hi>to come with an Army into</hi> England.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>If the Major and his Brethren muſt <hi>obſerve</hi> and note this as a piece of <hi>Novelty,</hi> which they knew not of before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the King did intend to bring in <hi>Forreigne Forces;</hi> me thinkes, the <hi>Exchange</hi> had been a fitter Theatre, then the <hi>Guild-Gall,</hi> to have call'd the Citizens together to have heard it, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle's</hi> heart needed not to <hi>bleed</hi> for that. But if they muſt <hi>obſerve</hi> and note this as a piece of <hi>Tyranny</hi> in the King, as a breach and violation of any knowne Law in the Land: (and to that end, it is moſt likely, he would have them to obſerve it,) Then truly does M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> deſerve to have his <hi>Noſe bleed,</hi> as well as his <hi>Heart;</hi> he deſerves to be well beaten, for offering ſuch a Cheat unto the Common People. For Gods ſake, why may not the King bring over <hi>Forreigners,</hi> when He ſhall be deſerted, and derelicted of his own <hi>Subjects?</hi> Why, may not the King invite <hi>Forreigne Forces</hi> hither, now at the laſt, for his <hi>Preſervation</hi> and <hi>Reliefe,</hi> whom the Rebels themſelves have entertain'd already, this two whole yeares and over for his <hi>Deſtruction</hi> and <hi>Ruine?</hi> I cannot imagine, why the <hi>worthy Citizens</hi> of <hi>London</hi> are to note and obſerve this, as any unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing, unleſſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> will undertake to prove, that the King, by bringing in of ſuch Forces into the Land, does treſpaſſe upon their ſeverall <hi>Acts</hi> againſt <hi>Forreigners,</hi> which are of ſo great force in <hi>London;</hi> For I know no other Law written, againſt which He does offend.</p>
                  <p>For I demand; either it is lawfull for the King to defend himſelfe by Force, againſt thoſe that doe rebell againſt him, or it is not lawfull. If they ſay, it is not lawfull for him to defend himſelfe by Force, then have the Rebels the ſame argument againſt the King's raiſing of his <hi>Domeſtique</hi> Forces, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his owne Subjects here at home; which they have, againſt his bringing in of <hi>Forreigne,</hi> from abroad; For if it be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113157:5"/> not lawfull for him to <hi>defend</hi> himſelfe by Force, then is it not lawfull for him to raiſe <hi>any kind</hi> of Forces. If they ſay, it is lawfull for him to defend himſelfe by Force, then doubtleſſe, are all kind of Forces in themſelves equally lawfull. Becauſe in this great <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Defence,</hi> no body but the King himſelfe, indeed, is a proper <hi>Agent;</hi> All others, whether Perſons or Things, are but nearer or remoter <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> uſed and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by Him, for his beſt advantage; and therefore, he that ſaies, it is lawfull for the King to defend himſelfe againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, with a native <hi>Engliſh</hi> or a <hi>Welch</hi> man, but not with a <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>French</hi> man; not with a <hi>Turke</hi> or <hi>Jew:</hi> and thinkes he hath ſpoken high reaſon to the point that is in queſtion; He ſaies nothing more in effect, then this: That, it is lawfull for the King to defend himſelfe againſt the Rebels, with an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sword, but not with a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Blade; or, that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him to ſhoot powder at them, which is made for him here in <hi>England;</hi> but not to ſhoot that, which is ſent him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, out of <hi>France.</hi> Or laſtly, that it is lawfull for him to charge the Rebels upon a Horſe, that hath been bred for him here at <hi>Brackley,</hi> but not upon a Horſe that hath been brought him over hither, from <hi>Barbary.</hi> For, as all ſorts of Weapons, ſo all kinds of men, are but the Kings Inſtruments in this great <hi>Action</hi> of his <hi>Defence;</hi> and it is as lawfull for him, to uſe the <hi>One</hi> for his defence, as to uſe the <hi>Other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which is there added, concerning the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain's</hi> eſtimation and power in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his complying with the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> is meere <hi>froth</hi> and <hi>fume.</hi> For, does not all the World know, that the Rebels themſelves care not, out of what quarter of the Compaſſe the wind blow, ſo it doe but hoyſe the Sayles up of their ſeditious Deſignes? Alas! there needs no <hi>breaking</hi> up of Cabinets, or forcing <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Letters, to come by this Intelligence, which all the World knowes; namely, that at this very inſtant, the Rebels have their <hi>Factors</hi> and <hi>Agents</hi> with the King of <hi>Spaine:</hi> and the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> queſtionleſſe is a Prince full of as great eſteeme at <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> can be; And that he complies faitely with the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> too, there is more then a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113157:6"/> ſuſpition, or a ſaying; For it is notoriouſly knowne, that the Rebels of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who have ſo often exclaym'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh'd againſt the King, for <hi>ſuspending</hi> the execution of Law againſt Recuſants, as if he ſavoured of <hi>Popery:</hi> have themſelves notwithſtanding, at the ſollicitation and inſtigation of ſome Agents for the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> pardoned two <hi>Jeſuites</hi> of late, out of their pure zeale unto the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The next thing that I ſhall obſerve to you, are Endeavours to overthrow the Law of the Land by Power, to repeale the Lawes and Statutes of this Realme by Force and Armes. Endeavours by Force and Armes, to repeale all the Statutes of this Kingdome againſt Papiſts. I ſhall read a paſſage to you, which you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard out of one of the Kings Letters to the Queene. The Letter was dated the fifth of</hi> March, 1644.</p>
                  <p>I give thee Power in my Name to promiſe, that I will take away all the Penall Statutes in <hi>England,</hi> againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, aſſoone as God ſhall enable me to doe it; ſo as by their meanes, or in their Favours, I may have ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſiſtance as may deſerve ſo great a Favour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When we Conſider that the Statutes of this Kingdowe againſt Papiſts muſt be taken away by Force; when we conſider that the Lawes of this Kingdome are to be Repealed by Power: who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but when he calls to mind the Declarations that have been made to put the Lawes in execution againſt Papiſts; of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, that have been made, and have been often made, to maintaine the Lawes of this Kingdome, who can chuſe but greive to thinke of it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>I remember a report that goes of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtigated once in a dreame to make ſome Verſes, was very much afflicted the next day when he awak't, how he ſhould doe it. For, accounting <hi>Poeſy,</hi> nothing but <hi>Colour</hi> and <hi>Fiction,</hi> and having been himſelfe all his life long, a profeſt Votary to <hi>Truth:</hi> He found that he wanted the faculty of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113157:6"/> making <hi>probable Lyes;</hi> and therefore he went and took <hi>Aeſops Fables,</hi> which he knew to be nothing elſe but <hi>Fictions</hi> ready framed to his hands, and put them into Verſe: that he might in ſome manner ſatisfie the will and pleaſure of his <hi>Inspiration.</hi> You ſee, <hi>Socrates</hi> was much troubled here to make <hi>Verſes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not <hi>lye;</hi> But, if you doe but ſever and divide theſe Complicated aſperſions, which are here caſt upon the King, you will eaſily ſee, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> is not much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled how to <hi>lye,</hi> becauſe he makes not <hi>Verſes:</hi> for, in all that hath been ſaid here, there is not ſo much as one tittle of <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Truth,</hi> that colours for a <hi>Crime.</hi> The principall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients to this <hi>Oleo</hi> of malice, are three; Firſt, that the King endeavours to overthrow the <hi>Law</hi> of the Land. Secondly, that he endeavours to overthrow that Law by <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Armes:</hi> and thirdly, That he endeavours to doe both, notwithſtanding all his <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> which have been made, unto the contrary.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of theſe, If, by <hi>Overthrowing the Law of the Land</hi> be meant a totall eradication and extirpation of all the Ancient <hi>Lawes</hi> which are of the <hi>Foundation</hi> of this Kingdoms <hi>Government,</hi> as if the King purpoſed to new mould the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and to let nothing paſſe for <hi>Law,</hi> but what he <hi>likes;</hi> Then, that which is here ſaid, is very <hi>conſiderable</hi> indeed, and to the purpoſe, but it is not <hi>true.</hi> For I hope, no man of underſtanding, will ſuffer himſelfe to be convinced by this Argument; The King will take away all the <hi>Penall Lawes</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which have been made againſt Recuſants: Therefore the King will take away all the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that ever have been made. And if, by <hi>Overthrowing</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> be meant onely the <hi>Suspenſion,</hi> or the <hi>Annihilation</hi> of ſo much of the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> as concernes <hi>Recuſants,</hi> and was made, but ſince the beginning of the laſt <hi>Queenes</hi> Raigne; Then, that which is here ſaid, is indeed very <hi>true,</hi> but it is no whitt <hi>conſiderable,</hi> or to the purpoſe. For, againſt what Law is it, to have a purpoſe or a reſolution to <hi>Repeale</hi> any Law? Certainly, the Lawes made here in <hi>England,</hi> are not like the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> that never muſt be <hi>changed.</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113157:7"/> They may be ſometimes abrogated by <hi>conſent;</hi> they may be ſometimes abrogated by <hi>diſſuetude,</hi> and <hi>diſuſe;</hi> They may be ſometimes abrogated, by continuall <hi>contrary Practiſes,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage;</hi> And thoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> which ſeem to have the beſt and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> are notwithſtanding ſubject to this juſt <hi>Fatali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that they never live longer, then their <hi>Reaſons.</hi> And then, doubtleſſe, if there be no ſinne in the <hi>Repeale</hi> it ſelfe of any Lawe, there can be no very great offence, in the <hi>Reſolution</hi> of Repealing.</p>
                  <p>I take not upon me now, to meddle with the <hi>Religion</hi> of thoſe Lawes, which were then made againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> or how farre it may be, or, may not be Lawfull, to uſe <hi>outward violence,</hi> in matters that concerne <hi>inward</hi> perſwaſion, (although, I profeſſe, I am apt enough to think, that, that is not <hi>Religion,</hi> which doth <hi>force</hi> men to <hi>Religion;</hi> and, that thoſe men, who by the ſence or expectation of any thing which is <hi>evill</hi> to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, as <hi>fining, impriſoning,</hi> or the like, doe endeavour to compell the <hi>Will</hi> of man to an aſſent of thoſe concluſions, whereof he is not, in the leaſt meaſure convicted, in his <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,</hi> doe but only let him ſee, that they want better argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.) I look only now, upon the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> why thoſe Lawes were made. And certainly, thoſe Lawes were not made, to determine the <hi>Truth</hi> of thoſe poynts in controverſie, which then were, and ſtill are, between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> for if ſo, then doe we our ſelves, ſtrike againſt a worſe rock, then that which hath already ſhipwrackt them; for whereas, they only make their <hi>Church,</hi> we make our <hi>State,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. The State may <hi>make</hi> Lawes againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> and yet that, which thoſe <hi>Recuſants</hi> doe believe and teach, may be <hi>True;</hi> and the State may <hi>repeale</hi> Lawes made againſt <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> and yet that, which thoſe <hi>Recuſants</hi> doe believe and teach, may be ſtill <hi>falſe;</hi> And, it is no better argument, to ſay, the King will repeale all the Lawes made againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> therefore the King is a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> then it is to ſay; the King will make no <hi>Lawes</hi> againſt the reading of the <hi>Alcaron,</hi> therefore the King is a <hi>Turke.</hi> The making or unmaking of <hi>Lawes</hi> of this nature, having no naturall Influxe, upon the <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Falſhood</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113157:7"/> the Things, or that conception, which thoſe men have of thoſe things, who make that Law; but only, upon the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences</hi> or <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> of Times. The neceſſity then, of thoſe preſent times, was the reaſon of the making of thoſe Lawes; the <hi>Queenes</hi> perſon was in danger from the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques;</hi> and that danger, was ſo much the more, becauſe thoſe <hi>Catholiques</hi> could not well be knowne. To <hi>diſcover</hi> them, and to <hi>defend</hi> her ſelfe, were all thoſe Lawes enacted; and, as God would have it, they did that, for which they were made; they diſtinguiſht <hi>Traytors</hi> from good <hi>Subjects;</hi> they made her <hi>lov'd</hi> of the one, and <hi>fear'd</hi> of the other: and ſo between both, ſhe continued a long and proſperous Reigne amongſt us.</p>
                  <p>But now, the Tables are clean turn'd. And the <hi>Kings</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is more in danger from a peſtilent faction of <hi>Schiſmatiques,</hi> then ever the <hi>Queen</hi> was, from her <hi>Catholiques.</hi> So that, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>reaſon</hi> of thoſe Lawes, there can be no great offence, if the <hi>Lawes</hi> themſelves, now, be made to ceaſe; and other Lawes eſtabliſht againſt thoſe kind of men, of whom the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King is ſo notoriouſly knowne to be in great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill and danger.</p>
                  <p>Well: the thing it ſelfe being thus clear'd, that any Law made may be <hi>Repeal'd:</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> doth not erre in the <hi>Matter</hi> of his promiſe, when He bidds the <hi>Queen</hi> promiſe in His name, that he will <hi>take away all the Lawes in England, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Recuſants;</hi> (provided they ſhall deſerve ſo great a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour at His hands) for he promiſes nothing, but what may be performed, without any breach of any known <hi>Law</hi> of the Kingdom whatſoever. All the ſcruple is, that he hath erred in the <hi>Manner</hi> of it; and that in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſte's</hi> opinion, theſe two wayes; firſt <hi>privatively,</hi> by ſecluding thoſe, that <hi>have</hi> the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Abrogation</hi> with him, that is <hi>both His Houſes of Parliament,</hi> and aſſuming the power wholly to <hi>himſelfe;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the words of His Letter doe runne thus, I <hi>will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>ſo ſoon as God ſhall enable</hi> me <hi>to doe it.</hi> And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Poſitively,</hi> by ſuperinducing thoſe, that have <hi>no</hi> right of <hi>abrogation,</hi> either <hi>with</hi> him or <hi>without</hi> him, and that is, <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Armes;</hi> becauſe he ſpeaks in his Letter, of ſome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113157:8"/> 
                     <hi>powerfull aſſiſtance,</hi> which ſurely can be meant of nothing elſe, but of <hi>Armes</hi> and <hi>Forces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the truth is, it is neither ſo, nor ſo. For firſt, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His excluding of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> Is any man ſo ſimple, as to think the King is bound, to write every private <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Complement,</hi> in that ſevere ſtile, and clogging forme, as if he were to write an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> and to choake up every line, with [<hi>The Kings Majeſty, by the Advice of his Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled</hi>] as often as occaſion offereth him diſcourſe, of the Tranſaction of any Parliament affaires? Nothing can be plainer, then, that the King, in ſaying, <hi>I will take away the penall Lawes,</hi> implyes the Power of the Parliament, as virtually comprehended in <hi>Him;</hi> and meanes, that He will <hi>doe</hi> it, in a <hi>Free convention</hi> of Parliament, and as it ought, for to be <hi>done:</hi> and therefore, if you marke it, he addes, <hi>as ſoon as God ſhall enable me to doe it;</hi> which words, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to ſuch a <hi>Convention,</hi> or they have no meaning. For, if the King had a meaning to repeale theſe Lawes <hi>without</hi> his Parliament: or could thinke, that He could <hi>Lawfully</hi> ſo <hi>doe;</hi> Certainly He might have <hi>done</hi> it long ere this; God hath <hi>ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> Him, with <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Might,</hi> anſwerable to the compaſſe of many ſuch Deſignes. (and for my part, if He ſhould doe it to morrow (though I am confident He never will, yet) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I ſee what the Rebells have to object againſt it; For I would faine know, why the King may not repeale the <hi>Lawes</hi> againſt <hi>Recuſancy, without the Parliament,</hi> as well and as farre forth, as the Parliament Repeales the Lawes for the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and for <hi>Epiſcopacy, without the King.</hi>) But, <hi>the Kings Power, loveth Iuſtice,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes; and<note place="margin">Pſal. 99. 4.</note> he conſidereth not his <hi>Might,</hi> ſo much as his <hi>Right;</hi> and, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, knowing well enough, that He cannot lawfully doe it, but <hi>in</hi> Parliament, He preſumes ſo farre upon the affections and gratitude, of all His true hearted Subjects, as to promiſe the Catholique party, that, in their names, <hi>out</hi> of a Parliament, which he doubts not, but the better eloquence of ſucceſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this preſent Rebellion, by meanes of their Aſſiſtance, will make appeare reaſonable <hi>in</hi> it, to performe.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113157:8"/>
                  <p>Nor does this any way croſſe ſhinnes with thoſe <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> which the King hath made, if a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man have the laying of them both together. For, what if the King have, upon ſome occaſions, made a <hi>Declaration,</hi> to put the <hi>Lawes</hi> in <hi>execution</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts?</hi> Surely, their ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and jealouſies owe him more thanks, for that inanima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which no doubt procured it. But, did the King, ever make a <hi>Declaration,</hi> that, upon no occaſion whatſoever, He would conſent to the <hi>Repealing</hi> of thoſe Lawes? If He did not, then certainly, the King may <hi>Declare</hi> that the <hi>Lawes</hi> againſt Recuſants ſhould be put in <hi>execution,</hi> for <hi>one</hi> Reaſon at <hi>one</hi> time; and yet conſent, that thoſe very <hi>Lawes</hi> ſhould be <hi>repeal'd</hi> for <hi>another</hi> Reaſon, at <hi>another</hi> time: His <hi>Religion</hi> all this while being the ſame, although his <hi>Reaſon</hi> be not. For his <hi>reaſon</hi> for the one, was but their <hi>ſuſpition;</hi> His <hi>reaſon</hi> for the other, is his own <hi>ſafety:</hi> which certainly is the better reaſon of the twaine; in regard, that the obligation, which is upon the King, to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of a peeviſh ſort of People; as he did in the one, is but a <hi>Temporall</hi> obligation; but that which is upon the King, to provide for His own <hi>ſafety,</hi> and the ſafety of all his good Subjects, as he did in the other, is an <hi>eternall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King hath made <hi>Declarations</hi> in behalfe of the <hi>Starre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber,</hi> and of the <hi>Common Prayer:</hi> and yet the Rebells are well contented, He ſhould quite <hi>abrogate</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> and at this inſtant, are as angry with him, that He will not <hi>aboliſh</hi> the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> nay, it is yet within the memory of Man, ſince our deare brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were eſteemed and accounted <hi>Rebels,</hi> by a <hi>Declaration,</hi> and yet theſe men, never yet queſtion'd, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd the King for Accepting and Treating with them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, like honeſt <hi>Subjects.</hi> When they have a purpoſe to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> the Lawes made concerning <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> then, every <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Oath</hi> which the King hath made againſt it, is eſteemed but a <hi>Gnatt:</hi> but when they have a purpoſe not to <hi>Repeale</hi> the Lawes made againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> then, every <hi>Declaration</hi> made for executing of thoſe Lawes, becomes a <hi>Camell.</hi> This is juſt the trick of the <hi>Jugglers books,</hi> that ſo amazes Country People and Children; which being turn'd one way, ſhewes you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113157:9"/> but Men or Womens <hi>Faces,</hi> but being turn'd the other way, is as full of horned <hi>Beaſts,</hi> or <hi>Divells.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then, as touching the Kings <hi>Proteſtations</hi> which have been often made to <hi>maintaine the Lawes</hi> of this Kingdome; for God's ſake, what of them? If they meane, That, becauſe the King proteſteth to <hi>maintaine the Lawes</hi> of the Kingdome, therefore he cannot <hi>repeale</hi> any one of thoſe Lawes whom he hath proteſted to <hi>maintaine?</hi> why then, doe they preſſe him to repeale divers and ſundry Laws, made concerning <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Common Prayer?</hi> ſeeing they are Lawes, which he is bound to <hi>maintaine,</hi> by this <hi>Proteſtation?</hi> But, if the meaning of thoſe wordes be, That, the King proteſteth to <hi>maintaine</hi> the Law, which is eſtabliſht for Law, to be ruled by that Law, and to doe nothing in an <hi>arbitrary</hi> way, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that Law (as no doubt, that is the meaning of his words) then does not the <hi>repealing</hi> and <hi>abrogating</hi> of any Law, thwart and croſſe his <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of <hi>maintaining</hi> the Law; becauſe, when it is <hi>Repealed,</hi> it is no longer a <hi>Law;</hi> And, as the <hi>Divines</hi> uſe to ſay, that our <hi>Saviour,</hi> when he came and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the dead mans Coffin, offended not againſt the Law, which holds ſuch Perſons uncleane; becauſe he purpoſed to reſtore him againe to life: So does not the king offend againſt His <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of <hi>maintaining</hi> the Law of the Land, if upon good occaſion offered, he ſhould a little ſuſpend the Execution of thoſe Lawes made againſt Recuſants for the preſent; which hereafter a <hi>free Convention of Parliament,</hi> will find as good occaſion wholly to take away, if their Aſſiſtance of the King in this his preſent exigence and neceſſity, ſhall appeare to them, ſo vigorous and hearty, to deſerve ſo great a Favour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third thing (Gentlemen) that I ſhall obſerve to you, is concerning the uſe and the ends that have been made, (which you may obſerve out of theſe Letters) of a Treaty with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. I ſhall read His Majeſties words to you in a Letter of the fifteenth of</hi> Febr. 1645. <hi>a Letter to the Queene.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And be confident, that in making Peace, I ſhall ever ſhew
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113157:9"/> my Conſtancy in adhering to Biſhops, and to all our Friends, and not forget to put a ſhort period to this perpetuall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And in his Letter to the Queene of the ninth of</hi> Febr. 1644. <hi>there is this paſſage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be confident, I will never quit Epiſcopacy, nor the Sword.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We did all hope, that the end of a Treaty had been to ſettle a happy Peace, a firme and a well grounded Peace: But now we ſee by the Kings Letter, that his Reſolutions are, ſtill to keep the Sword in his owne hands. We did all hope, that the end of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was to ſettle Church-Government according to the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Solemne Vow and Covenant, which we have all taken. But you ſee by the Kings Letters, that he avowes to the Queene, that he will never quit Epiſcopacy. We did all hope, that the end of a Treaty was rather to confirme the Parliament, then to diſſolve it; But the King ſayes in his owne Letter, that he will not forget at this Treaty, to put a ſhort period to this perpetuall Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Here is a very fine Rhetoricall <hi>Rainbow;</hi> much, is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>ſhewe,</hi> nought, in <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> knew well enough to whom he ſpake; to the common ſort of People, <hi>Qui fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentèr in hoc ipſum fallendi ſunt, ne errent,</hi> as <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſpeakes of them: who are alwayes to be <hi>couſened,</hi> and even for this very purpoſe, often, That they may not be <hi>deceiv'd.</hi> For I dare ſay, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> is no more perſwaded, in himſelfe, of the truth of theſe particular Aſperſions, which are here caſt upon the King, then <hi>Theopompus,</hi> when he changed cloathes with his wife, and ſcaped out of priſon, could beleive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a woman, becauſe he made the keepers to beleive it. We will only divide, a little, between his <hi>Concluſions</hi> and his <hi>Clouds,</hi> and then, you will the more eaſily perceive it. One of the <hi>Concluſions</hi> which he takes upon him to perſwade, and worke in the minds and affections of the people, is this: That <hi>the King never intended Peace in the last Treaty.</hi> The <hi>Cloud</hi> which is caſt about that <hi>Concluſion,</hi> to cover it from their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113157:10"/> underſtandings, is this. Becauſe his Reſolutions are, ſtill, to keep the <hi>Sword</hi> in his owne hands. Now, the People can doe no leſſe, then ſubſcribe to this Propoſition, as being neceſſarily true: He that is reſolved to <hi>keep the Sword</hi> ſtill in his hands, is reſolved not to have a <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the double acceptation of that notion, [the <hi>Sword</hi>] would eaſily diſpell this <hi>Cloud,</hi> and ſpread it into nothing. For the word <hi>Sword,</hi> as well in Sacred as in Civill Writers, as it ſometimes implyeth the <hi>materiall Sword,</hi> that Inſtrument of violence, wherewith one private man ſmites and hurts ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of which our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaks in the Goſpell, when he ſaies unto S. <hi>Peter, Put up thy Sword;</hi> So doth it other whiles imply the <hi>Civill Sword,</hi> or, that power and adminiſtration of Iuſtice, which reſides in the Supreme Magiſtrate, and inflicts ſeverall puniſhments on ſeverall perſons, according to their ſeverall offences; of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in his Epiſtle, when he ſaies of <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperour, that, <hi>He beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi> Now, nothing can be playner, then, that the King uſeth that word [<hi>Sword</hi>] in this latter Acceptation; and, as by <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> They cannot but acknowledg, that the King under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands that old Forme of <hi>Hierarchicall</hi> Government, in the Church now eſtabliſht, which he tells the Queene he will not <hi>quit,</hi> for that of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which is the new Fangle; So they cannot deny, without denying their reaſon, that, by the [<hi>Sword</hi>] which the King there joyneth with <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> He meanes that <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Forme of Government in the <hi>State</hi> now eſtabliſht; which He tells the Queene, He will never <hi>quit</hi> for a <hi>Democracy,</hi> which the <hi>Rebels</hi> labour ſo hard to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinduce upon him; And then, this horrid <hi>Concluſion</hi> having broken thus through the <hi>Cloud,</hi> reſolves, into leſſe then a <hi>mans Hand:</hi> for, it reſolves <hi>into no more but this:</hi> The King never intended to change the preſent Government of the <hi>Church,</hi> or the preſent Government of the <hi>State;</hi> Therefore the King in the laſt Treaty <hi>never intended Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, what needed the Queenes Letters to be broken up for this? Did not the King's Commiſſioners, when they were at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> tell you the very ſame thing <hi>twenty dayes</hi> together?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113157:10"/> that, the King would not alter the Government of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> unleſſe there were better <hi>Reaſons</hi> urged, then your bare <hi>wills?</hi> how comes this then halfe a yeare after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to be told the good Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> for ſuch newes? Alas! you muſt thinke, They have brought up the men of <hi>London</hi> (who, by nature, were never very fierce) to ſuch a tameneſſe of underſtanding, that they muſt needs think every thing a great <hi>Secret,</hi> and of ſome <hi>myſterious</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in the <hi>Queenes</hi> Letters; and therefore, they care not at how deare a price of <hi>Inhumanity,</hi> they purchaſe it. Not much unlike the ſimple fellow, ſpoken of in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who gave<note place="margin">Lucian.</note> three hundred pence for one of <hi>Epictetus</hi> his Candles endes, which was not worth three halfe pence; becauſe he had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that he could not chuſe but prove an excellent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, if he ſtudied never ſo little by <hi>Epictetus's</hi> Candle.</p>
                  <p>And, of as great Conſequence, that is, juſt of none at all, is that which followes, where the King ſayes, <hi>He will not forget at this Treaty, to put a ſhort period to this perpetuall Parliament.</hi> And I ſhall only ſay this to it; He that is offended with the King for deſiring to put an end to this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> that another of better temper, and affection, may be Summo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; let him groan unpittyed, under the preſſures and miſeries, which from this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> he ſuffers, and ever will, ſo long, as this <hi>preſent</hi> Parliament endures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The laſt thing that I ſhall obſerve to you (for you will have the reſt obſerved to you by a better hand) is concerning the King's diſavowing this Parliament, to be the Parliament of England; We cannot have greater aſſurance of any thing from the King, then of this preſent Parliament; There is no Law ſtronger, that gives a property to the Subject, then the Law is, to continue this preſent Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is ſo well knowne to the World, that Kingdomes and States abroad acknowledge it, and now for the King to diſavow it, after it is confirmed and continued by Act of Parliament; after the King hath ſo lately acknowledg'd it, now ſo ſuddainly to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113157:11"/> diſavow it, How can we be more confident of any aſſurance or Act from His Majeſty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There be many things more obſervable in theſe Letters, but I ſhall leave them to thoſe worthy Gentlemen, that come after me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>It was a common practice of the <hi>Popes</hi> Emiſſaries, in the begining of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> when any <hi>conſidering</hi> or <hi>diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> man, began to ſpeake ought againſt the groſle <hi>Corruptions</hi> &amp; <hi>Impoſthumes</hi> in that See, (which were then as <hi>viſible,</hi> as that pretended <hi>Head</hi> it ſelfe, that bred them;) To brand him for deſerting the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> in ſome point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Beliefe;</hi> (that ſo, they might expoſe him to the greater igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie and danger) who, good man, only diſtaſted the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> in ſome poynt of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Manners;</hi> And by this cunning artifice, they maintained the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the height of all her villanies and impieties: no man, for a long time, daring to oppoſe them. In like manner deale the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells with the King. The King diſtaſts a factious and ſeditious <hi>Party,</hi> grown too potent in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> a Party, which have <hi>frighted</hi> moſt of the honeſt Members that are preſent, and <hi>forced</hi> away more of them that are abſent; and therefore, are no more a <hi>Parliament</hi> indeed, then a nut, is a nut, where the <hi>maggot</hi> hath eate out the <hi>Meate;</hi> and this diſtaſting of this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent <hi>Faction in</hi> this Parliament, is branded by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle,</hi> for a diſavowing <hi>of</hi> this <hi>Parliament,</hi> to be a <hi>Parliament,</hi> on purpoſe to draw the greater <hi>odium</hi> upon the King; who, I think, is as rare in this <hi>unhappineſſe,</hi> as in many of his <hi>Vertues,</hi> that he is, not only the firſt <hi>King,</hi> but the firſt <hi>Man,</hi> that ever yet wenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to perſwade the People, and to let them ſee, they were not <hi>well govern'd,</hi> and could not be <hi>believed.</hi> The King diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avowes not this <hi>Parliament;</hi> nor any one <hi>Act,</hi> that ever He yet paſt this Parliament; no, not ſo much, as that <hi>Act,</hi> which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues</hi> this Parliament; although perchance, he may think that Act as lyable to a <hi>Repeale,</hi> as any other; and ſo for diverſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, may <hi>repeale</hi> it; Nay, in endeavouring and reſolving to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> it, he does acknowledge it an <hi>Act.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113157:11"/>
                  <p>And whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> thinkes, he hath ſtruck this ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous aſperſion home into their Memories, with this <hi>hammer</hi> of his Eloquence, that <hi>There is no Law ſtronger, that gives any Property to the Subject, then the Law is to continue this preſent Parliament.</hi> I ſhall only interpoſe and lay this <hi>ſoft</hi> Reply be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, to dead the <hi>noyſe</hi> and <hi>fury</hi> of the Blow; and that is this: That, if the <hi>Law</hi> to continue this preſent Parliament, were no <hi>ſtronger,</hi> then any Law; which I know in the Kingdome, which gives any <hi>Property</hi> to the Subject, is; The King need not take ſuch care to put a <hi>period</hi> to it; For, as <hi>they</hi> have done, it would ſoon <hi>ceaſe,</hi> and <hi>vaniſh</hi> of it ſelfe, and come to <hi>nothing;</hi> The <hi>ſumme totall,</hi> indeed, of all, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> hath ſaid. And therefore, as <hi>Demosthenes</hi> uſed to ſay of <hi>Phocyon,</hi> when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſaw him riſing up to ſpeak; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">Demoſth.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold, here riſes the Hatchet of all my words;</hi> and ſo would goe no farther. So does M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> at the ſight of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate,</hi> who is now riſing. and if the Citizens <hi>heads</hi> ſhould prove ſo hard <hi>all over,</hi> that neither <hi>Hammer</hi> nor <hi>Hatchet</hi> ſhould doe any good upon them, it were very ſtrange: but commonly, where there are <hi>two</hi> men that have <hi>Malice</hi> enough which is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of a Scandall; there will be <hi>twenty,</hi> that will afford <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity</hi> enough, which is the <hi>Mother.</hi> And no doubt, but ſo it hapned here.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> his Speech.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Letters are ſo full, that I ſhall rather be your</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer, <hi>of what you have heard in them, then give you any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Then does this Speech come <hi>after</hi> thoſe Letters, like an Eve <hi>after</hi> an Holy-day; which ſhould have come, <hi>before</hi> it; For, ſure I am, thoſe Letters are not ſo <hi>Full,</hi> but this ſpeech is as <hi>Empty.</hi> I begin to have a conceit, that theſe <hi>three</hi> honeſt men, had a dangerous plot in their heads, and that was, to make <hi>one</hi> good Orator between them. For M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> ſeems to be diſpoſed of, in the <hi>Middle Region,</hi> where Rhetorick is <hi>coldeſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113157:12"/> and where the Lawes of <hi>Oratory</hi> doe indulge moſt <hi>remiſneſſe</hi> and <hi>relaxation;</hi> for this very purpoſe, that, according to their ordinary diſtribution of Preaching-houres, the <hi>Major and his Brethren,</hi> may be <hi>ſilent,</hi> at the beginning, till they have uſed themſelves a little to heare ſence; may <hi>Cenſure</hi> the latter end, as being the only part of the ſpeech which they remember; and may <hi>ſleep</hi> about the middle, while M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> the <hi>City-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer,</hi> may proceed in his <hi>new</hi> office, without more Interruption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhall preſent before you a very ſad ſpectacle, The whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of</hi> Ireland <hi>bleeding, a Kingdome all in Peace without any thoughts of Warre, without any thoughts of Armes; and of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, a Popiſh Partyriſing up, laying hold upon all the Forts, ſeizing all the Lands, and all the Goods of the Proteſtants in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and not content with that, when they had done, killing one hundred thouſand of them, Man, Woman, and Childe. Theſe Rebels of</hi> Ireland, <hi>that had thus inhumanely murthered ſo many Proteſtants; (here is the ſadneſſe) Now the Favourites of the King, and thoſe Subjects that the King did profeſſe to maintaine, in maintaining Armes againſt thoſe Rebels; We that by Acts of Parliament of the Kings owne Grant, had the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebels Lands and Territories granted to us, to maintaine a Warre againſt them; now becauſe we maintaine that Warre, we are Rebels and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebels, becauſe that they ſtand againſt you, They ſhall be freed from all Penall Lawes, They ſhall have any thing that They deſire, nothing is too deare for them, any Lawes may be altered for their ſakes: But when the Proteſtants come to deſire an Alteration of Law for the advancement of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and for the ſettlement of the Proteſtants, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be granted to them by a Proteſtant King, but every thing to the</hi> Iriſh. <hi>I ſhall ſay but a word more, and pray conſider of it; The Condition why all this is granted to the</hi> Iriſh, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to you, it is onely this; That the</hi> Iriſh <hi>may come over into</hi> England, <hi>to cut your Throats, as they cut the throats of all the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Proteſtants in</hi> Ireland. <hi>This is the cauſe, for which they are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113157:12"/> encouraged to come hither. If there be ſuch a reward for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, if there be ſuch a fruit of the Proteſtations of the King, what can we expect?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Truly, the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland bleeding,</hi> were a very ſad ſpectacle, did not the Kingdome of <hi>England bleeding,</hi> call for both our Eyes. A Kingdome, before <hi>this</hi> Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, ſo growne aged in continuall Happineſſe, that, as they uſe to ſay of the ſpiced and perſum'd Ayre, in which the <hi>Sabeans</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Agatharo.</note> live, <hi>Summus quidem odor, ſed volupt as minor;</hi> The very <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi> ſeem'd to abate the <hi>pleaſure;</hi> and the <hi>Repetition</hi> of nothing but the ſame <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> which were ſtill, as conſtant, as their <hi>Dayes,</hi> did not ſo much <hi>affect</hi> the Sence of the Nation, as <hi>dull</hi> it. When, on the ſuddaine, an <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> Party riſing up, layes hold upon all the Kings <hi>Forts,</hi> and <hi>Ships,</hi> ſeizes all His <hi>Lands,</hi> rifles all the <hi>Goods</hi> of moſt of the Proteſtants in <hi>England:</hi> and not content with that, hath opened more then one hundred Thouſand Veynes, of as good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> bloud, and made of as good milke, as ever the Church of <hi>England</hi> gave, ſince She lay in of her firſt <hi>Reformation.</hi> Now, theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of <hi>England,</hi> that have diſpoyled their owne lawfull <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> of all his Royall <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and juſt <hi>Rights,</hi> and that have thus inhumanely murthered ſo many thouſands of their owne <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Brethren, (<hi>here is the ſadneſſe</hi>) avow themſelves the <hi>loyall</hi> and moſt <hi>obedient</hi> Subjects of the King; and thoſe Subjects, who venture their Lives and Fortunes in the Cauſe of God, and of the King, Thoſe, they traduce for <hi>Malignants, Traytors,</hi> and <hi>Rebels.</hi> God forbid, that the King, or any good <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſhould juſtifie that Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> halfe ſo much, as theſe <hi>Engliſh Rebels</hi> themſelves doe, that exclaime moſt againſt it; For aſſuredly, no man <hi>juſtifies</hi> a ſinne more, then he, that does <hi>commit</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>When the Rebellion brake out firſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> all the world knowes, there was no man in <hi>England</hi> more forward in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſenſe of his Indignation againſt it, then the King. Both Houſes of Parliament, could not ſuggeſt any probable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113157:13"/> 
                     <hi>Expedient</hi> for the quenching of that <hi>Flame,</hi> but the King ſtraight way ratified and approved <hi>it.</hi> Nay, His <hi>Induſtry,</hi> was ſo, like His <hi>Intereſt,</hi> farre tranſcending theirs, that, whileſt they were only hovering about <hi>Advice;</hi> He was upon the wings of <hi>Action,</hi> and would have interpoſed his own Sacred Perſon in the Quarrell, if they would have allowed it, and thought it fit. But, now that a greater <hi>Flame</hi> is kindled in the Bowells of this Kingdome, and, that thoſe very <hi>Buckets,</hi> which, <hi>there,</hi> ſhould have caſt on <hi>water,</hi> to have quenched it, are <hi>here,</hi> caſt on themſelves, to augment and raiſe the <hi>fire;</hi> he, that will blame the Kings affections for being <hi>corrupted,</hi> becauſe they are a <hi>little coold;</hi> He that will accuſe Him, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>falſe</hi> to the Principles of <hi>Law,</hi> which bindes Him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend His Subjects againſt the Rebells in <hi>Ireland;</hi> becauſe He is <hi>true</hi> to the Principles of <hi>Nature,</hi> which binds him to defend himſelfe, againſt the Rebells here in <hi>England:</hi> Certainly, that man will approve his <hi>Humor</hi> for <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> who, when the fatall Axe hung over him, took greater care for his <hi>Haire,</hi> then for his <hi>Head.</hi> And therefore, M. <hi>Tate</hi> addes little to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of his Cauſe, when he heapes up theſe exaggerations upon the King; That, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebells, can <hi>be freed from all the penall Lawes,</hi> that they, <hi>may have any thing which they deſire;</hi> and, that <hi>Nothing is to deare for them &amp;c.</hi> for the more <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> and <hi>deare</hi> the conditions are, on which the King pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes the ſettlement of <hi>Irelands</hi> Peace; The more <hi>infamous</hi> and <hi>odious</hi> is this Treaſon and Rebellion here in <hi>England,</hi> which alone hath <hi>rais'd</hi> the <hi>Market:</hi> For, if <hi>England</hi> would not <hi>Pipe</hi> ſo as it does, <hi>Ireland,</hi> would have but little mind to <hi>Dance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> is of opinion, that all this is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that they may come over into <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>cut Throats;</hi> Truly I am of opinion, that if they doe not make more haſt, then I can yet perceive they doe, they will looſe their Labour; for the <hi>Scots</hi> will have done their <hi>Worke,</hi> before they come. Whoſe encouragements no doubt, are the better of the twaine: For, what they looſe in gay <hi>promiſes,</hi> they find in good <hi>Pay.</hi> What they have not in <hi>Repealing</hi> of <hi>Lawes;</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113157:13"/> they have, in <hi>Reaping</hi> the profit of good <hi>Lands.</hi> What they want in three or foure <hi>Complements,</hi> They have in five <hi>Counties;</hi> And a <hi>Scott</hi> that will not <hi>cut Throates</hi> upon theſe Tearmes, let him live by <hi>cutting of Purſes:</hi> or, (which is more <hi>Merchant-like</hi>) by <hi>ſelling of Pinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All I have to ſay is, you ſee you muſt ſtand to your Armes, and defend your ſelves; For there is no hopes for you, unleſſe you can ſubmitt your necks to the Queene, and be transformed into Iriſh Rebels, and Papiſts. I know not how you can obtaine any favour at Court, eſpecially having ſuch a Mediator as you have, a Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that is ſo hated by the King. As long as that mediates for you, you ſhall have nothing; but if you can have a Popiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Queene to ſollicite in your behalfe, you ſhall have any thing. I know you are too much Engliſhmen, and Proteſtants, to ſubmit to ſuch baſe conditions: Therefore lay aſide all diviſion, and unite your ſelves in this Cauſe, that you may be Maſters of the Popiſh Party, that otherwiſe will kill you all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Are you come to ſay <hi>all that you have to ſay</hi> already? I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt a very moderate Gentleman; and one, that is not like to be a <hi>Lecturer</hi> long; for, though he knows not <hi>what</hi> to ſpeak, yet he knowes <hi>when</hi> to hold his Tongue. I will undertake, after this rate, he might have talkt till mid-night. But ſir, doe you thinke your Aldermen are awake? or rather, doe not you think that you have talkt all this while, in your ſleep? For my part, I confeſſe, I am ſo farre a Citizen of the <hi>Common Hall,</hi> that I doe not underſtand you; and I take it for a great bleſſing upon mine Innocence, that I doe not reach your meaning. The truth is, I doe a little ſuſpect, that, if the matter were well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, you that paſſe for one of the <hi>Speakers</hi> here, would prove rather, one of the <hi>Sybills,</hi> who they ſay, neuer underſtood their owne Prophecies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quintilian</hi> obſerves, that there are ſome <hi>ſtreynes</hi> in <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, quae fortia ſunt, dum laedunt, ſtulta verò cum laeſerint,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113157:14"/> which are <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>able</hi> to <hi>doe</hi> miſcheife in the minds of men, and then are as <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>ſimple,</hi> when they have <hi>done</hi> it: as if ſome kind of Rhetorique had that operation on the <hi>mind,</hi> which ſome Phyſick hath upon the <hi>body;</hi> That opens and looſens it, when you take it, and then tyes and binds it up as faſt, when it is taken; And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> is excellent at theſe <hi>ſtraines.</hi> I warrant you, when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> did but cry, <hi>ſtand to your Armes</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and <hi>defend your ſelves;</hi> the Citizens could imagine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, then that Sir <hi>Colebrand</hi> would forſake his <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers place</hi> about the <hi>Clock-houſe,</hi> and come amongſt them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently like a <hi>Clubb man.</hi> No queſtion, but when he tells them of <hi>ſubmitting their Necks</hi> to a <hi>Popiſh Catholique</hi> Queene (you may ſee, his words coſt him nothing, he is ſo liberall to give us two for one) the Citizens could not take the <hi>Queene</hi> for leſſe, then a <hi>She-Tamberlaine,</hi> and began to think, that if ſhe would needs tread upon <hi>their necks,</hi> ſhe might chance hurt her feet. I dare ſay, when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate</hi> told them, they muſt be <hi>Transformed into Iriſh Rebels, and Papiſts;</hi> the Londoners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to conſider, whether it was not againſt their Charter, and Liberties, that any body ſhould <hi>transforme</hi> them, beſides their owne Wives. So, are ſimple men affected, and wrought upon, they know not with what, more, then with what they know, as woemen, and Children are more affrighted with a <hi>naked</hi> Ghoſt, then with an <hi>Armed</hi> man.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch another <hi>Raw head and bloody bones</hi> is that <hi>Popiſh Party,</hi> which, if they <hi>be not maſters of</hi> betimes, <hi>will kill them all.</hi> in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tates</hi> opinion; though truely how they ſhould be maſters of them, I doe not well ſee; for this <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Horſe, Foot, and ſome Dragoones; The <hi>Horſe</hi> flye in the <hi>ayre,</hi> and have lately taken a great <hi>Caſtle</hi> there; The <hi>Foot,</hi> march <hi>under ground;</hi> and have made <hi>wooden</hi> Ordinances, of moſt of <hi>Middletons Pipes;</hi> and the Dragoones, ſwim with their matches in their mouthes, and have nothing but their very bare heads above the <hi>water.</hi> Why, but harke you my maſters, will this cruell <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> have no more pitty, then to <hi>kill them all?</hi> what, <hi>fee, fa, fum?</hi> man, woman, child and all? what? not leave ſo much as <hi>one</hi> Alderman and his wife, for the City
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113157:14"/> Government to <hi>Breed on?</hi> what? not let <hi>one</hi> Lecturer <hi>run up to ſeed,</hi> againſt another yeares Rebellion? No, not ſpare a man: you <hi>ſhall be killed</hi> All; and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate,</hi> to my thinking, hath end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>Speech,</hi> as the Country Fellowes did their <hi>Play,</hi> who kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one another ſo faſt; till they left never a man <hi>living,</hi> to conclude it; So that, I know nothing elſe is to be ſaid, but <hi>Sound Drums and Trumpets,</hi> and <hi>exit</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Tate,</hi> carrying <hi>off the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> his Speech.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord</hi> Major <hi>and you worthy Citizens of the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>I ſhall not trouble you to repeat any of the Letters, that you have heard read; I doubt not, but you that heard them, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member moſt of them: only this I will ſay to you; That for my part, I know not whether we have more cauſe of Joy or Sorrow, for this which this day you have heard. Cauſe I know, we have to be ſorrowfull, that things are ſo ill with us, as they are: And I am ſure we have Cauſe to rejoyce, that things are now diſcovered and brought to light, that have been ſo long hid in darkeneſſe. This is a day of diſcovery. Heretofore thoſe that ſpake thoſe things, that you have heard this day manifeſted vnto you, were accounted the Malignant Party. They were tearmed Rebels, they were ſuspitious jealous People without Cauſe. The Lords and Commons in Parliament, they have heretofore declared their feares of the things, that you now ſee proved; Anſwers have been given to thoſe Feares, with ſlights and ſcornes. Things are this day diſcovered to you, that were enjoyned to be kept ſecret, by the ſtrongeſt engagements; The goodneſſe of God giving ſucceſſe to our Army hath brought theſe things to light.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>The Rebels at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in opening theſe pretended <hi>myſteries</hi> of darkneſſe to the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, have proceeded in that manner, by the way of <hi>method;</hi> which <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> in opening a darke place of Scripture to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Jerome,</hi> is related to have proceeded in, only by the way of <hi>mirth.</hi> For, being importun'd by him, to know the meaning of thoſe words in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Luke.</hi> Now <hi>upon the ſecond Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113157:15"/> after the firſt;</hi> of which words even <hi>Nazianzen</hi> himſelfe, knew not the proper meaning: He bid him come to Church next Sunday, when he Preacht, and then; he would tell him; becauſe he knew, that although he himſelfe ſhould not be <hi>able</hi> to give <hi>Jerome</hi> any <hi>ſatisfaction:</hi> yet then, and there, he knew well enough too, that <hi>Jerome</hi> would not be very <hi>willing</hi> to give him any <hi>Reply.</hi> They are now growne ſo cunning at the <hi>City-Cheat,</hi> that they will never ſhew any Stuffes willingly, but by their owne <hi>Lights.</hi> And their <hi>Two</hi> great <hi>Lights,</hi> are; <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Speeches,</hi> like the <hi>Sun,</hi> to rule the <hi>Day:</hi> and <hi>Bells</hi> and <hi>Bonefires,</hi> like the <hi>Moone,</hi> to governe the <hi>Night;</hi> and, by theſe <hi>Lights,</hi> are the <hi>Maſques</hi> of moſt of their <hi>Thankeſgivings,</hi> ever acted. What a preparation is here made to ſome great <hi>Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity?</hi> what Occaſions and Cauſes of Joy, preſented, for ſome wonderfull <hi>Diſcovery?</hi> If the Title Page had not told us, that this <hi>Speech</hi> was ſpoken, the <hi>third</hi> of <hi>July;</hi> who would not have thought, it had been made, for the <hi>fifth</hi> of <hi>November?</hi> when in very deed, the fowleneſſe of the <hi>matter</hi> here diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, does no more expiate, that fowler unworthineſſe of the <hi>meanes</hi> uſed in the diſcovery: then that famous <hi>Italian</hi> Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could anſwer, his killing of a man; by making a good Picture of a man, newly killed. But, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> knowes, he is, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> was in his Pulpit, where he may ſay any thing, and not be contradicted; and, (as the Fellow in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who had wraſtled with one that had a good <hi>Tounge,</hi> and given him a ſound <hi>Fall:</hi> when, he was ask't who had the better on't, anſwered, it was very uncertaine, becauſe, ſaies he, although I am ſure, that I had the better in throwing him, yet he hath the better of me, in denying it, and perſwading of the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, there was no ſuch matter: So) the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> although, by the light of their owne underſtanding, they ſee well enough, that there is nothing of moment in theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Letters, but what the King may openly juſtifie to God, and to the World: Yet, when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> obſerves ſuch horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> unto them; when he tells them of ſuch <hi>Secrets</hi> brought to <hi>light,</hi> as were to be concealed by the <hi>ſtrongeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements</hi> of Faith and Love; They begin to think it ſo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113157:15"/> forgetting, that it is as eaſie a matter, for a <hi>French Cook,</hi> and a <hi>Committee-man,</hi> to make a <hi>Feast</hi> out of a <hi>Straw,</hi> as it is an ordinary thing, for themſelves, to make a Solemne <hi>Funerall,</hi> when there is nothing in the <hi>Coffin,</hi> but a <hi>Faggot.</hi> But, let us heare, what theſe <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> are.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Before His Majeſty departed from the Parliament, the Lords and Commons by a Petition to him, did preſent unto him their Feares, occaſioned by the favouring of Recuſants; Their Feares, that he would bring in Forreigne Forces; That he would change and alter the Lawes. They gave him their Reaſons for all: But he was pleaſed to give his Anſwer with denying all, as they affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all. For that of Forreigne Forces, becauſe he gave a punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Anſwer to that, I will tell you what it was. When they told him, that they were informed that the Popes Nuncio did deale with the French and Spaniſh Kings, to ſend to him, 4000 men a peice, the King did Anſwer to them,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it was improbable in it ſelfe, and Scandalous to him, for which he deſired Reparation at their hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And at another time, he anſwers that very poynt concerning Forraigne Forces, poſitively, and ſaith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No ſober, nor honeſt man can believe, that we are ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, or ſo ſenceleſſe (<hi>they are His very words</hi>) to entertaine ſuch a deſigne, as to bring in Forraigne Forces, which would not only bring this Our Kingdome in diſtraction and Ruine, but Our own name and Poſterity in perpetuall Scorne and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have heard what hath been ſaid for that; you have heard his own Letters how He deales with the Queene, and how preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing He is with Her, to bring into this Kingdom; the Duke of</hi> Lorraine <hi>with his Army. The Duke of</hi> Lorraine <hi>you know, is a Catholique, Popiſh, Forraine Prince. So you ſee how much He is alter'd from what He thought then, and how His endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are now; that both Honest men, and Sober men, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that He would doe it, becauſe He writes to Her, with ſuch earneſtneſſe, to pray Her to doe it for Him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113157:16"/>
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>The ſcope and purpoſe of this Paragraph, is to expoſe His <hi>Majeſty</hi> to the reproach of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>Contradiction,</hi> by committing ſome of His <hi>open</hi> Anſwers and Proteſtations, with ſome of His <hi>Private</hi> Inſtructions and Letters; and to make them claſh together, in the poynt of <hi>Forraigne Forces.</hi> And truly, if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> had done this, he had done ſomething; that is, if M. <hi>Browne</hi> had evidently demonſtrated this, that the King at the very ſame time, and being in the very ſame ſtate and condition, when He profeſſed <hi>openly,</hi> that <hi>no Sober or Honeſt Man could believe He was ſo desperate,</hi> or <hi>ſenſeleſſe, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch a deſigne, as to bring in Forraigne Forces;</hi> had <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately</hi> notwithſtanding, &amp; by Letters under hand, ſolicited the Queen for Forces from the Duke of <hi>Lorraine;</hi> This indeed had caſt a blemiſh upon His <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Honour;</hi> This had clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, one of the brighteſt <hi>Stones</hi> in all the <hi>Crowne;</hi> for <hi>nihil eſt, quod clariore lumine praefulgeat, quam recta fides in Principe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hotoman.</note> ſaith the great Lawyer: There is nothing of that <hi>Luſtre,</hi> like a Princes <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi> This had been a plaine breach of Faith and Honeſty; to which nothing could have been ſaid, by way of modification or excuſe, that could have rendred it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Honourable</hi> or <hi>Lawfull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, if M. <hi>Browne</hi> only demonſtrate this, that the King at <hi>one</hi> time, and being in <hi>one</hi> condition, profeſſed againſt <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Force;</hi> and then, that, at <hi>another</hi> time, and being in <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> condition, he preſſed the Queene for it: I believe, this will not amount to any <hi>fault,</hi> if it be <hi>ſtrictly</hi> conſidered; much leſſe, to any <hi>Falſhood.</hi> For, what doe they take the meaning of thoſe words of the Kings to be; That, <hi>no ſober nor honeſt man can believe him ſo desperate or ſo ſenceleſſe, to entertaine ſuch a deſigne, as to bring in Forraigne Forces?</hi> Either they muſt take thoſe words, in the nature of a bare <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> expreſſing for the time to come, the Kings mind, as it was at preſent; and ſo, to juſtify the uprightneſſe of ſuch an <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that a man meanes <hi>as</hi> he ſpeakes, <hi>when</hi> he ſpeaks, and not, that he ſhould continue <hi>alwaies</hi> in that meaning. For a man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113157:16"/> hath <hi>power</hi> and <hi>right</hi> too, to change his mind; And, if, in that <hi>change</hi> and <hi>alteration</hi> there be any thing that is <hi>ill,</hi> (as often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it falleth out, there is) That <hi>evill,</hi> is no way intrinſecall to the <hi>mutation;</hi> but it ariſeth from the <hi>matter;</hi> namely, when the <hi>firſt</hi> opinion was better, then the <hi>ſecond</hi> is; ſo that, unleſſe M. <hi>Browne</hi> can prove, that the King had a mind to bring in <hi>Forraigne Forces,</hi> at that very time, when He profeſſed He had no ſuch thought, or entertain'd any ſuch deſigne, His <hi>Aſſertion</hi> remaines entire, and without fault, notwithſtanding any change or alteration of His mind, which ſince might happen to it. Or, they muſt underſtand thoſe words, in the nature of a <hi>contract</hi> or <hi>promiſe,</hi> which obliges the King, not only for the preſent, to meane what he ſaies; but for the future, to continue in that meaning; and if ſo, then, there are two ſeverall Rules in the Civill Law, which would be conſidered: for, they will acquit the King from the diſreputation of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> or breach of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;</hi> notwithſtanding his endeavours by the Queene, to bring in <hi>Forreigne Forces.</hi> The firſt Rule, is this: <hi>Omnis promiſſio habet in ſe tacitam conditionem hans, Rebus ſic ſtantibus: &amp;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Menoch.</note> 
                     <hi>aliquo, de novo, non ſuperveniente.</hi> That is, Every <hi>Promiſe,</hi> hath this tacite <hi>Condition,</hi> implyed and involved in it, of [<hi>Things being as they were</hi>] when the <hi>Promiſe</hi> was made; for, if there be any notorious change or mutation in the <hi>Condition,</hi> either of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> or <hi>Things;</hi> A man is not then, ſaith the Law, obliged by his <hi>Promiſe.</hi> And, is there not a remarkable <hi>Alteration</hi> of both, in our preſent Caſe? Are not both the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> changed, and the very <hi>Things?</hi> when the King promiſed he would entertaine no <hi>ſuch deſigne, as to bring in Forreigne Forces,</hi> he promiſed that to <hi>Subjects,</hi> and in the time of <hi>Peace;</hi> but, they that clayme this promiſe of him now, are <hi>Rebels,</hi> and they claime it, being themſelves againſt him, in an open <hi>Warre:</hi> And is not this a ſad <hi>Change,</hi> and <hi>Alteration?</hi> when the King promiſed, not to <hi>bring in Forreigne Forces,</hi> the thing was a matter of <hi>Indifferency:</hi> for, the King was in no viſible danger, but that he might have ſubſiſted well enough without them; But now, when they claime it, it is a matter of <hi>neceſſity:</hi> and for ought any man knowes, the onely viſible way, under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113157:17"/> left to the King for to defend himſelfe; And is not this s ſenſible <hi>Mutation?</hi> therefore the <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Times, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and <hi>Things</hi> being <hi>changed:</hi> the <hi>Obligation</hi> of the promiſe alſo, ſaies the Law, is not in reaſon, longer to <hi>continue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Rule amongſt the Civilians is this: <hi>Quoties per alium fit, quo minus id impleatur, quod eſt promiſſum, habetur</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ell.</note> 
                     <hi>illud, quod promittitur, ac ſi fuiſſet impletum.</hi> When it is <hi>long</hi> of <hi>Him,</hi> only, to whom the promiſe is <hi>made,</hi> why it <hi>is not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> it is all one in equity, <hi>as if it were performed,</hi> according to that of the <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> who ſaies, <hi>perſolut â fide, quia per eum non ſtetit, quò minus preſtaretur,</hi> that is; as having <hi>diſcharged</hi> his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>promiſe,</hi> (ſaith he) becauſe it was not his fault, any<note place="margin">Liv: Hiſt.</note> way, that his <hi>Faith</hi> was not <hi>diſcharged.</hi> And was it not <hi>long of them,</hi> that the King did not <hi>keep</hi> his <hi>promiſe?</hi> He that cannot reach the cleareneſſe of this Truth, by reaſon of that eminent <hi>diſtance,</hi> between the <hi>people</hi> of a Kingdome, and the <hi>Prince;</hi> will comprehend it eaſily, brought neerer home unto him, by this familiar <hi>Inſtance</hi> and <hi>Example.</hi> A Maſter of a Family keeps many <hi>ſervants</hi> in his Houſe, and every man knowes what worke he hath to <hi>doe,</hi> and accordingly he <hi>does</hi> it. At laſt, being conſcious to themſelves, that their work went not on, ſo as it ſhould, a rumour and a whiſper flyes amongſt them from one unto another, that their <hi>Maſter</hi> meanes to retaine ſome <hi>Journey-men</hi> and <hi>Hirelings,</hi> of his <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and will have them <hi>lye</hi> together, and <hi>worke</hi> together, with his <hi>ſervants,</hi> that his worke may be the <hi>better</hi> and the <hi>ſooner</hi> done. Hereupon, they move their <hi>Maſter</hi> in the poynt, and declare unto him, that if He call in any of his <hi>Neighbours</hi> to the work, it would <hi>breed ill bloud;</hi> He muſt looke to have his houſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much <hi>diſordered,</hi> and his goods <hi>embeaſel'd,</hi> for none of his Servants <hi>would</hi> take charge of them, nor <hi>could:</hi> So many <hi>ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> comming in and out, that it was impoſſible. The <hi>Maſter,</hi> who was ſure to have the <hi>worſt</hi> of it, if any thing were <hi>loſt,</hi> is eaſily perſwaded hereunto, not having indeed the leaſt <hi>thought</hi> or <hi>Imagination</hi> of any ſuch <hi>thing:</hi> but (being a man of ſo much gentleneſſe and meekneſſe, as to let his <hi>owne</hi> Servants, take their <hi>owne</hi> times and wayes) of his owne free accord, he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113157:17"/> makes this <hi>ſolemne promiſe,</hi> to them, that <hi>no ſtranger ſhall come in to them,</hi> from amongſt his <hi>Neighbours,</hi> either to <hi>meddle</hi> with their <hi>worke</hi> or <hi>them.</hi> At laſt, theſe ſervants have a plott upon their <hi>Maſter,</hi> to <hi>take away his life:</hi> and to that purpoſe, they break up all his <hi>Cheſts,</hi> ſeaze upon all his <hi>Monyes,</hi> and are now <hi>forcing</hi> his owne Bed-Chamber <hi>Dore,</hi> to <hi>murther</hi> him. The good man perceiving their intent, tells them, that, if they offer to break open the <hi>dores</hi> upon him, he will call to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours out at the <hi>window,</hi> to ſend their <hi>ſervants</hi> in unto his help, and then their Villany, will be <hi>diſcovered,</hi> &amp; they, ſeverely <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> whereas if they will goe quietly to bed againe, He will ſay nothing of it, and for once, put the matter up. The <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> tell him againe, that they know he is an honeſt man, and ſcorns to <hi>break his promiſe:</hi> He promiſed them above a moneth agoe, that he would not <hi>ſuffer any ſtranger to come in to his Houſe,</hi> and they hope he will not offer, now, at this time of the night, to <hi>call</hi> them. If this man ſhould think himſelfe obliged by that promiſe, to let his owne <hi>ſervants</hi> come in, and <hi>cut his throate;</hi> Will not any man ſay, that he had more <hi>Conſcience,</hi> then <hi>Sence?</hi> For, the <hi>Maſter</hi> does not <hi>break</hi> his promiſe, but the <hi>ſervants</hi> will not ſuffer him to <hi>keep</hi> it. And, this is juſt the Kings Caſe, in the poynt of <hi>Forraigne Forces:</hi> which, if any dull Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of <hi>London</hi> will not underſtand, as it is delivered by <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> let ſome of his owne <hi>ſervants,</hi> beat it into his <hi>Braines,</hi> (as theſe <hi>ſervants</hi> would have done,) by a neerer <hi>Application.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For their Feares, of his making Warre againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of his alteration of Religion and Lawes, he hath heretofore in his Printed Declaration, expreſſed theſe words.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We doe againe, in the preſence of Almighty God, our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Redeemer, aſſure the World, that we have no more thought of making Warre againſt the Parliament, then againſt our owne Children; that we will maintaine and obſerve the Acts aſſented to by Vs this Parliament, without violation, and that we have not, nor ſhall not have any thought of uſing any Force, unleſſe we ſhall be driven to it, for the Security of our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113157:18"/> Perſon, and for the Defence of the Religion, Lawes, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdome, and the Iuſt Rights and Priviledges of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And in another of his Printed Declarations, he hath ſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God ſo deale with me and mine, as my Thoughts and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are upright for the maintenance of the True Proteſtant Religion, and for obſervation, and preſervation of the Lawes of the Land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And in another Declaration, he ſaith, that</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He is reſolved not onely duely to obſerve the Lawes Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but to maintaine them, againſt what oppoſition ſoever, though with the hazard of his being.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And in his Declaration, concerning his Reſolution to goe into</hi> Ireland, <hi>which is alſo Printed, he calls God to witneſſe, the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Profeſſions there made, with this aſſurance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That His Majeſty will never Conſent, upon what pretence ſoever to a Toleration of the Popiſh Profeſſion there; or to the abolition of the Lawes now in force againſt Popiſh Recuſants in that Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What could his Majeſty have ſaid more to ſatisfie his People? Now, compare his Actions with his Declarations; and compare his Letters to the Queene, with his Promiſe and Proteſtations to the Parliament, and you will ſay,</hi> Quantùm mutatus? <hi>how much is his Majeſty changed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All that we have heard read, we may divide into three parts. The firſt, containes the Letters, Propoſitions, and Tranſactions, concerning Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond, the Letters from the Queene to the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third, Letters from the King unto the Queene, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Here are three particulars more, laid to His Majeſties charge by M. <hi>Browne,</hi> wherein His <hi>private</hi> Letters, are made to croſſe and contradict His <hi>publique</hi> Proteſtations, that ſo with more colour, they may aſperſe him with the ſinne of <hi>Levity, Falſhood,</hi> and breach of <hi>Faith;</hi> by which <hi>eaſy wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> they hope to make him as <hi>vile,</hi> in all His <hi>Peoples</hi> eyes, as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113157:18"/> His own <hi>obſtinate Goodneſſe,</hi> hath made him <hi>cheap</hi> in <hi>theirs.</hi> The firſt is, concerning His <hi>making Warre</hi> againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; The ſecond is, <hi>concerning the Alteration of Religion;</hi> and the third is, concerning His <hi>Alteration of Lawes;</hi> Againſt theſe three, they produce His <hi>Proteſtations</hi> and <hi>Promiſes,</hi> which, they would have the world believe, He doth ſo directly check, by His private endeavours and practiſes; as if he eſteemed no more of what He promiſed, then that <hi>Aegyptian</hi> King, whom they nicknamed <hi>Doſo,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Dabo,</hi> becauſe he would<note place="margin">Diod. Sieul.</note> 
                     <hi>promiſe</hi> any thing which men asked of him, and would be as ſure, never to <hi>performe</hi> any thing unto them, which he had promiſed.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the firſt of theſe, His <hi>making Warre</hi> againſt the Parliament, (which is ſuch a <hi>thred-bare</hi> piece of <hi>malice,</hi> that, as it never had any <hi>Truth,</hi> ſo now, it hath worne away the very <hi>Sence</hi>) They preſſe thoſe words of His <hi>Declaration,</hi> which they conceive expreſly makes againſt it, wherein the King does aſſure the World, that <hi>He hath no more thought of making Warre againſt the Parliament,</hi> then, <hi>againſt His own Children;</hi> and, <hi>that he hath not, nor ſhall not have, any thought of uſing of any Force;</hi> unleſſe he ſhall be <hi>driven to it, for the ſecurity of his Perſon; and for the defence of the Religion;</hi> which words truly, doe condemne the King to my thinking, juſt as <hi>Pilate</hi> did <hi>Chriſt,</hi> namely, by <hi>waſhing of his hands;</hi> For, can any thing be plainer, then that, as thoſe tearms of Ampliation, <hi>We have not,</hi> nor <hi>ſhall not have, any thought,</hi> of <hi>uſing of any Force,</hi> doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend in them, a <hi>formall</hi> profeſſion, that the King <hi>will not</hi> wage Warre againſt the Parliament; ſo, thoſe words of Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and exception, <hi>unleſſe we ſhall be driven to it, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Perſon:</hi> doe contain in them a <hi>virtuall</hi> profeſſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that <hi>He will?</hi> And therefore, when M. <hi>Browne,</hi> will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the King, for <hi>making Warre</hi> againſt the Parliament, as <hi>doing</hi> contrary to His expreſſe <hi>Declaration;</hi> and will take no notice, of that <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Reſervation</hi> annexed thereto, (which, as expreſly juſtifies all that the King hath done.) He ſaies no more, in truth, <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>King;</hi> then the Welch-man did <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113157:19"/> the <hi>Iudge,</hi> who cryed out upon him, for putting him to death for ſtealing a <hi>Rope,</hi> but left out the <hi>Mare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning the ſecond, His <hi>Alteration of Religion,</hi> they produce theſe words out of another of the Kings Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: <hi>God ſo deale with Mee and Mine, as My thoughts and intentions are upright, for the maintenance of the true Proteſtant Religion:</hi> and thoſe words in His <hi>Declaration,</hi> concerning His going into <hi>Ireland:</hi> That <hi>His Majeſty will never conſent, upon what pretence ſoever, to a Toleration of the Popiſh profeſſion there, or the Abolition of the Lawes, now in force againſt Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants in that Kingdomes.</hi> And then, concerning the third, that is, His <hi>Alteration of the Lawes;</hi> the words of another <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> are remembred and caſt in His teeth; wherein He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes. That <hi>He is reſolved not only duly to obſerve the Lawes Himſelfe, but to maintain them againſt what oppoſition ſoever, though with the hazard of his being.</hi> And now, how <hi>falſe</hi> the King hath been to both theſe <hi>ſolemne</hi> Profeſſions, by His <hi>ſecret</hi> practiſes, let His Letters and M. <hi>Browne</hi> declare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning</hi> Ireland, <hi>you have heard the Propoſitions made to the Queene, for ſending into this Kingdome, diverſe</hi> Iriſh <hi>Rebells, under the command of two profeſſed Papiſts; ſix Thouſand of them were to be under the command of the Lord</hi> Glamorgan, <hi>the Earle of</hi> Worceſters <hi>eldeſt Son; the other of ten Thouſand, under the command of Colonell</hi> Fits. Williams: <hi>The tearmes that they were to come upon, were read to you in the Propoſitions; which themſelves ſent to the Queene. You will not thinke, that theſe came to maintain the Lawes, but to deſtroy them, not to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Proteſtant Religion, but to overthrow it; Theſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions being ſent to the Queene, and allowed by Her, and Shee ſent them to the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For, the Letters concerning</hi> Ireland, <hi>they were written by the King, to the Earle of</hi> Ormond, <hi>who is now Governor there; in ſome of them Letters, the King gives way to the ſuſpending of</hi> Poynings <hi>Law, which was an Act of Parliament, in the tenth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113157:19"/> yeare of</hi> Henry <hi>the ſeaventh. It was called</hi> Poynings <hi>Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sir</hi> Edward Poynings <hi>was Governor of Ireland, when that Law was made. That Law, made all Statutes, that were before made in England, of force in Ireland; and the King may as well ſuspend all the Lawes there as that Law. By that Law of</hi> Poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>all Lawes that were after to be preſented at the Parliament in</hi> Ireland, <hi>muſt be firſt ſent hither for approbation, before they could be preſented to the Parliament there; and no Parliament muſt be called there, before the cauſes of calling the Parliament, and the Acts to be paſſed in that Parliament, are firſt ſent hither and approved. But that Law now, muſt be ſuspended.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Further in the Letters to the Lord of</hi> Ormond, <hi>you ſee the King doth not count it a hard Bargaine; for to make a Law in</hi> Ireland, <hi>to ſuspend, or to take away the Penall Lawes, againſt Papiſts there, ſo that they will help Him here againſt His Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Subjects. When this promiſe was made, the Declaration was not remembred, wherein the King doth declare,</hi> that upon no pretence whatſoever, he will Tolerate the Popiſh profeſſion in Ireland, or Aboliſh the Lawes againſt Popiſh Recuſants, now in force there. <hi>He farther ſaith in another Letter to my Lord of</hi> Ormond, that rather then He will faile of making a Peace or a Ceſſation with the Rebells, He would have him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelfe to joyne with the Rebells againſt the Scots, and the Lord <hi>Jnchequin,</hi> which is the maine viſible Proteſtant For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are in Ireland: <hi>all this is enjoyned to be kept ſecret, from all but two or three of the chiefeſt Rebells in Ireland, whom you heard named in the Letters. You may farther obſerve, that a Peace was Treated of with the Rebells, about the ſame time, that the King did Treat with the Parliament here concerning Ireland; and the King wiſhed a quick diſpatch of the Peace there, leaſt if He ſhould make a Peace here firſt, He could not ſhew ſuch Favour to the Iriſh, as He intended: They are the words of His Letter. You may ſee by all the Letters to my Lord of</hi> Ormond, <hi>that the King did little stick at any thing, to grant to the Rebells for a Peace with them; but how little He granted to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> England <hi>at the laſt Treaty, I hope all the World will ſoon know.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113157:20"/>
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Here are <hi>two principall</hi> things offered by way of proofe, out of the Kings owne Papers concerning the Tranſaction of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to convince the King of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>breach of Faith,</hi> in two <hi>former Profeſſions.</hi> The firſt is, where he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth my Lord of <hi>Ormond,</hi> that He will <hi>ſuspend Poynings Law,</hi> which they ſay, croſſes and contradicts his Solemne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of <hi>maintaining</hi> the <hi>Lawes, againſt what oppoſition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> though, <hi>with the hazard of his being.</hi> And the ſecond is, that he propoſeth unto him. <hi>The taking away of all Penall Lawes made againſt Recuſants in Ireland:</hi> which, they ſay, is poynt-blanke againſt his owne <hi>Declaration,</hi> which he Printed, when he had a reſolution to goe over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein he does aſſure all his Subjects, That He will <hi>never Conſent, upon what pretence ſoever,</hi> to <hi>a Toleration of the Popiſh Profeſſion there, or the Abolition of the Lawes now in force, againſt Popiſh Recuſants in that Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And truly, the maine <hi>Engine</hi> of their detraction and Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, moves upon theſe two <hi>Hinges;</hi> Theſe two particular <hi>Impeachments,</hi> help and further all the reſt, to the <hi>Reputation</hi> of Crimes: as, one or two good peices of Wine, they ſay, will put off a whole range in the Merchants Sellar, at the ſame rate and value, with themſelves. Concerning the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Poynings Law;</hi> I muſt needs ſay, that, if it were <hi>True,</hi> that is, <hi>True,</hi> in that latitude of underſtanding, and vaſt Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sence, which the Rebels, would have the ſimple People ſwallow; The King were to be condemned indeed: not only, as a <hi>man</hi> falſe to his <hi>Conditions,</hi> but as a <hi>King</hi> falſe unto his <hi>Crowne:</hi> For, amongſt all thoſe <hi>Flowers,</hi> that at ſeverall times have been tranſplanted out of other <hi>Soyles</hi> into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crowne, there is ſcarce any one, that illuſtrates the <hi>beauty</hi> of her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with more vigorous and freſher <hi>Colours,</hi> then this very <hi>Law.</hi> Becauſe, that by this, and by no one thing ſo much as This, is the <hi>Subordination</hi> and <hi>Dependance,</hi> which <hi>Ireland</hi> hath <hi>upon this</hi> Kingdome eſtabliſhed, and the <hi>bluſh</hi> of her firſt <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> revived.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113157:20"/>
                  <p>For firſt, This <hi>Law,</hi> tranſported whole <hi>Colonies</hi> of other <hi>Lawes:</hi> So that, all the Statutes, which, were then made in <hi>England,</hi> like Trees with their ground about the rootes, were removed into that Kingdom, where they proſpered &amp; thriv'd, though in another ayre, as if, there, they had been firſt ſet, and planted. And the King were much too blame, indeed, if he thought of <hi>ſuſpending</hi> this part of that <hi>Law:</hi> For, this were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to lay the reynes upon the Horſes neck, for feare leaſt he ſhould ſlip the bit out of his mouth; This were, to ſet open the Priſon <hi>dore,</hi> for feare the Priſoner ſhould make ſome eſcape out at a <hi>window:</hi> This were, to breake that whole <hi>Chaine</hi> of dependance, which unites <hi>that</hi> Kingdome in her ſubordination to <hi>this,</hi> to prevent ſome men, from looſning of a <hi>linke.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, By this <hi>Law,</hi> there could no <hi>Law,</hi> be preſented to the Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be confirmed and ratified <hi>as a Law:</hi> unleſſe it were firſt ſent hither into <hi>England,</hi> for the Kings <hi>Approbation,</hi> before ever it was propoſed; And this part of that <hi>Law,</hi> was not intended, ſo much, for an Abaſement of the <hi>Subjects</hi> Liberty, as for an Allay, unto the <hi>Superiour's</hi> Power: to put the <hi>Deputies</hi> in mind, ſtill, that their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was not <hi>Abſolute.</hi> And truly, if the King had promiſed to <hi>ſuspend</hi> this part of that <hi>Law,</hi> (although it was ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that thoſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> would put any thing, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd the <hi>Superiours</hi> Advantage, into the <hi>Subjects</hi> Scale) The King had not done well; for, as in making the picture of a Crowne, there is more Art uſe to paint it in <hi>Colours,</hi> ſo that it ſhall look <hi>like</hi> Gold, then to paint it, in <hi>pure Gold,</hi> indeed: So, in making <hi>Lievtenants</hi> which are but <hi>Counterfeits</hi> of Kings; there is more Policy, to embelliſh them with the <hi>ſhadowes</hi> and <hi>ſemblances</hi> of Royalty, then with the Reall <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, the King promiſes neither this, nor that; as the words of<note place="margin">Letter. XVI.</note> his Letter plainly doe declare; and the truth of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is but briefly this. A Peace in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was now in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the King wrote theſe Letters to my Lord of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond:</hi> and the neceſſities of the Kings Affaires, called for all quick <hi>dispatch</hi> therein; That diſpatch, the King apprehended, as it was indeed, altogether <hi>Impoſſible:</hi> if every particular Bill,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113157:21"/> upon every particular emergent occaſion, which might facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and expedite that work, muſt firſt be ſent hither, and then ſent back again, with the King's <hi>Approbation</hi> to it, before ever it could paſſe in Parliament, (as the <hi>letter</hi> of that <hi>Law</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires) the paſſage being ſo obſtructed as it was; and the wayes ſo dangerous. And therefore the King, in favour of thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, the quick tranſaction whereof, ſo neerely concerned the good of both his Kingdomes, promiſed my Lord <hi>Ormond,</hi> to take no advantage againſt him, by <hi>Poynings</hi> Law, if he paſſed ſuch Bills, as might promote this buſineſſe, <hi>without ſending them over unto him:</hi> provided, he paſſed nothing that might be prejudiciall to the <hi>ſafety of His Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> and the <hi>preſervation</hi> of <hi>His owne Royall Authority;</hi> And, this <hi>particular</hi> ſuſpenſion, of this <hi>particular</hi> Branch, of <hi>Poynings</hi> Law, limited to this <hi>particular</hi> Time, and to be no farther extended; doe the Rebels aggravate and heighten to a <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion</hi> of all <hi>Poynings</hi> his <hi>Law:</hi> yea, and of all the <hi>Lawes,</hi> that were ever there made beſides; as if the King purpos'd, to deſtroy them all, at one blow, and without any more adoe: without any the leaſt regard had to His Solemne <hi>Declaration,</hi> and <hi>Promiſe,</hi> for the <hi>maintaining</hi> thereof.</p>
                  <p>But, is this a <hi>Croſſing</hi> and <hi>Contradicting</hi> of the Kings owne words in his <hi>Declaration,</hi> where he promiſes to <hi>maintaine the Lawes againſt what oppoſition ſoever, though with the hazard of his being?</hi> I cannot think it. For, I aske but this; Of what kind of <hi>Lawes,</hi> will a reaſonable man conceive, that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty there ſpeakes? queſtionleſſe, not of thoſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne His <hi>owne</hi> Royall <hi>State, Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Dignity,</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, thoſe are as true and as neceſſary <hi>Lawes,</hi> as any other) becauſe, it is not imaginable, that the People ſhould ſuſpect, that He would <hi>not maintaine them:</hi> But, of thoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> which concerne the Subjects <hi>Intereſt, Right,</hi> and <hi>Property;</hi> as being moſt lyable to their ſuſpition, that the King, by His <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> or by ſome <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>unnaturall</hi> Courſe or other, might entrench too much upon <hi>them.</hi> Now, what colour of <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> or <hi>Falſhood,</hi> is there in this Inference; The King, by a <hi>ſecond Promiſe,</hi> undertaketh to diſpence with a rigorous
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113157:21"/> circumſtance of <hi>one</hi> Law, which only diminiſhes and mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates a little, the <hi>Grandour</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of his <hi>owne Royall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>Dignity;</hi> therefore the King breaks his <hi>first Promiſe,</hi> of <hi>maintaining the Lawes againſt what oppoſition ſoever,</hi> which only concerne His Subjects <hi>Interest,</hi> their <hi>Liberties,</hi> and their <hi>Property.</hi> There is nothing plainer, then that both theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, may well conſiſt together, without claſhing. But, if the <hi>Lyon</hi> ſay, that the <hi>Foxes eares,</hi> are <hi>hornes;</hi> The <hi>Foxe</hi> hath more wit then to <hi>gaineſay</hi> it: And, if the Rebels at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> ſay, that the ſigne of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Laurences</hi> paralell'd <hi>gridiron,</hi> is the ſigne of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Peters</hi> Croſſe <hi>Keyes,</hi> the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> have ſo little wit, as not to disbeleive it. But any man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, may now eaſily diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Past<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board,</hi> and the <hi>Vizard,</hi> and make him mirth with <hi>that,</hi> in his owne <hi>hands,</hi> which affrighted him, but a little before, upon anothers <hi>Face.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In that other Impeachment of <hi>Aboliſhing the Lawes made againſt Recuſants in Ireland,</hi> notwithſtanding His former <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,</hi> that He would <hi>never</hi> doe it; I confeſſe, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which hath the <hi>colour</hi> and <hi>complexion</hi> of a Crime, at the firſt <hi>bluſh,</hi> and at a <hi>diſtance;</hi> and therefore, I ſhall deſire leave, to come a little <hi>nearer</hi> to it, and to look better upon it, in the diſquiſition of theſe enſuing <hi>particulars</hi> and <hi>pieces;</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, cannot but diſcover it, if there be any thing, truly <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall,</hi> within it. Firſt, we will conſider, whether the <hi>Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> made againſt Recuſants, be <hi>in it ſelfe,</hi> a thing that is <hi>unjuſt;</hi> Secondly, we ſhall conſider, how farre, it may become ſo, by the Kings <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Proteſtation</hi> to the contrary; And laſtly, we ſhall conſider, how farre that <hi>Promiſe</hi> does <hi>bind</hi> and <hi>tye up</hi> all other <hi>contrary</hi> Promiſes, which may be made upon <hi>contrary</hi> reaſons and enducements, for feare, either of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> or <hi>Injuſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt, it is out of queſtion, that all <hi>Penall Lawes,</hi> are but <hi>Obligations</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> perſons to <hi>ſome</hi> puniſhments, with relation to <hi>ſome</hi> Actions or Omiſſions, which, either have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an <hi>intrinſecall pravity,</hi> by reaſon of the immutable <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the thing; or elſe, an <hi>extrinſecall obliquity,</hi> by reaſon of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113157:22"/> ſome contrary <hi>Command.</hi> Now, if <hi>Refuſall</hi> of <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be confeſſed an <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of the former ſort, that is, an Omiſſion, which in the very <hi>nature</hi> of the Thing, were <hi>intrinſecally</hi> vicious or evill (and ſuch an <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> it may be, to refuſe <hi>to worſhip God;</hi> but, to refuſe to <hi>worſhip</hi> him, after <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> manner, will hardly riſe unto it.) yet would it not ſtraight way follow, That becauſe it is <hi>Juſt,</hi> that offendours in that kind, ſhould be <hi>puniſhed,</hi> therefore the Supreme Magiſtrate is <hi>unjuſt;</hi> that inflicts no <hi>puniſhment</hi> upon them. Becauſe, we are to know, that <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> does not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes follow upon the <hi>not doing,</hi> of what is <hi>Juſt.</hi> For, as it does not follow, that, becauſe a Prince is <hi>liberall,</hi> if he give a Penſion of a thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> to one, that is a well deſerving Servant, at his hands; Therefore, he is <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>illiberall,</hi> if he give him not a <hi>penny;</hi> So, neither is it perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally true, That, that <hi>thing,</hi> which is very <hi>Juſtly</hi> done, cannot be, but <hi>uniuſtly,</hi> let alone; as we ſee, in the caſe of <hi>Blasphemy:</hi> which the King might <hi>iuſtly</hi> puniſh with death, if he ſhould make a Law againſt it; as the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did: and yet, we doe not ſay, He is <hi>uniuſt,</hi> becauſe He does not doe it.</p>
                  <p>But, if <hi>Refuſall</hi> of <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> prove but an <hi>Omiſſion</hi> of the ſecond ſort, that is, an Omiſſion of a thing, which hath nothing of <hi>Evill</hi> in it, further then <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall denomination,</hi> as being the <hi>Reſult</hi> of ſome poſitive Law or other, that does <hi>command</hi> it; Then, certainly, the ſame power that <hi>enacted,</hi> may <hi>aboliſh</hi> it: <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> not being any whit eſſentiall to any poſitive Law, to <hi>continue</hi> it unto the <hi>end;</hi> but <hi>Power,</hi> that it may be ſeverely kept, and may reach thoſe <hi>Eudes,</hi> for which it is <hi>continued.</hi> And therefore, the very Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, by the light of reaſon could obſerve, that nothing<note place="margin">Sopat. Epiſt. ad Demet.</note> was more eaſily <hi>dispenſable,</hi> then <hi>Penall Lawes;</hi> It being the <hi>priviledge</hi> of all <hi>Authority,</hi> whether <hi>Divine, Civill, Paternall,</hi> or <hi>Deſpoticall,</hi> upon emergent occaſions, in things which are <hi>Indifferent,</hi> to make <hi>Lawes,</hi> and ſo by conſequent, <hi>ſinnes:</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding the leaſt <hi>entity</hi> to the things themſelves, which continue ſtill the <hi>ſame,</hi> whether they be <hi>commanded</hi> one while, or, another while, <hi>forbidden.</hi> And, that <hi>Communion with the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113157:22"/> Church of England,</hi> in the <hi>manner</hi> of Gods <hi>worſhip,</hi> is but a Thing, in its owne <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>before the Law</hi> commanding it, <hi>Indifferent;</hi> will eaſily be made appeare, by this: that, as ſome Perſons are <hi>puniſhable</hi> by Law, that doe <hi>refuſe</hi> it (as, in our preſent caſe, of ſuch men who are <hi>Recuſants:</hi>) So, are other perſons <hi>puniſhable</hi> by Law, that <hi>uſe</hi> it; (as, in the caſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>excommunicate;</hi>) which could never certainly be done, if the Thing it ſelfe, were in its owne nature, <hi>Evill.</hi> For, the State might as well command a man, to <hi>forſweare</hi> himſelfe three or foure <hi>dayes</hi> together, or to <hi>commit Adultery,</hi> three or foure <hi>nights</hi> together, by way of <hi>puniſhment,</hi> for ſome prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Sinne;</hi> as, to command him, not to <hi>Communicate with the Church of England,</hi> in her <hi>publique worſhip,</hi> if this <hi>not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating,</hi> had that <hi>Intrinſecall pravity,</hi> rooted in the very <hi>nature</hi> of the Thing, which, that <hi>Forſwearing,</hi> and <hi>committing of Adultery,</hi> are acknowledged to have in <hi>them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But thoſe Lawes, which in themſelves are <hi>mutable,</hi> and ſubject to <hi>abolition,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> (whether we ſpeak of that which is <hi>unjuſt</hi> in <hi>nature,</hi> or of that, which is in <hi>Law</hi>) may notwithſtanding become <hi>Immutable,</hi> theſe two ſeverall wayes, either by <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Promiſe.</hi> For every <hi>Oath,</hi> is a ſigne of <hi>Immutability</hi> brought upon that thing to which an <hi>Oath</hi> is added: The Apoſtle is plaine for it, who telleth us, that <hi>God willing to ſhew the Immutability of his Councell</hi> (in the 6. Heb. 17.) <hi>confirm'd it by an Oath;</hi> That, by <hi>two Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things, &amp;c.</hi> And a <hi>promiſe,</hi> does give ſuch a <hi>right</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> to the Party promiſed, that, without <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> it can not be taken from him. Now, becauſe, although it be in the <hi>free Power</hi> of the Magiſtrate to <hi>make</hi> ſuch a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> yet, it is not in his <hi>Power</hi> to break that, which He hath freely <hi>made;</hi> therefore, we reckon, that a promiſe <hi>not to abrogate</hi> a Law, does adde and imprint an <hi>Immutability,</hi> in that very Law; and ſuperinduces a legall <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> upon it, ever to be <hi>abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> or <hi>changed.</hi> In the ſecond place therefore, let us ſee, what that <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi> was, which the King did make, againſt this <hi>Abolition;</hi> and how farre, the ſaid <hi>Abolition</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>unjuſt,</hi> by vertue of that <hi>Promiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:113157:23"/>
                  <p>When the Rebellion firſt brake out in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>expedients,</hi> which were ſuggeſted by the Parliament of England for the ſuppreſſion thereof, proved not ſo dextrous, and happy when they came to <hi>Action,</hi> as they ſeemed, when they were but in <hi>Deſigne:</hi> The Kings Majeſty, to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall honour of His <hi>Innocence,</hi> who was aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſed, as having ſome kind of ſecret <hi>Influence</hi> upon the <hi>Revolt</hi> of that whole Kingdom, made this offer to His two Houſes, that He would expoſe himſelfe to the danger of an <hi>expedition</hi> thither, in his own ſacred <hi>Perſon,</hi> if they would think it fit, and make a Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if He could <hi>reduce</hi> it. And, becauſe the <hi>guiltineſſe</hi> of their <hi>own</hi> intentions, prompted them to a baſe <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of <hi>His;</hi> as if He might uſe ſome meanes of <hi>Reduction,</hi> more prejudiciall to the Crowne, then the <hi>Revolt;</hi> by, permitting a <hi>toleration</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Profeſſion, to the <hi>Catholick party</hi> there; (who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, had been uſed to a gentle connivence from the ſupreme Magiſtrate in the poynt of Conſcience, ever ſince the firſt Reformation of this Church:) His Majeſty, for the cleare ſatisfaction of His two Houſes, and of all His Subjects, in their unworthy miſinterpretations, and murmures; and, for the juſtification of the <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of His Reſolutions and deſignes in this preſent <hi>expedition,</hi> and <hi>adventure;</hi> Opens Himſelfe in a <hi>Declaration</hi> to all the World; and amongſt other particular expreſſions of a ſincere Heart, and cordiall affection to <hi>Gods</hi> cauſe, and His <hi>Owne:</hi> He gives them this <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> that, if He does goe over in Perſon, as He does intend; <hi>He will never conſent, upon what pretence ſoever, to a Toleration of the Popiſh Profeſſion there; or, the Abolition of the Lawes now in force against Popiſh Recuſants, in that Kingdome.</hi> Inſomuch, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> does well, to rejoyne unto thoſe words of the Kings <hi>Declaration,</hi> theſe of his, <hi>What could His Majeſty have ſaid more to ſatisfy His people?</hi> For, by this <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>not aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing thoſe Lawes,</hi> he hath inveſted his People, with ſuch a <hi>Right</hi> in thoſe Lawes; that, he cannot <hi>eaſily,</hi> nay, he cannot without <hi>Injury,</hi> ever take it from them; unleſſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, will. And there is no queſtion in the World, but if the King had, <hi>at that time</hi> gone over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and had aſſented
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113157:23"/> either to a <hi>Toleration</hi> of the <hi>Catholique Religion;</hi> or, had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven way to the <hi>Abolition of thoſe Lawes then in force againſt Recuſants,</hi> upon any Tearmes whatſoever, which the witt of man could imagine be moſt Honourable, or Advantageous, either to him or to his Kingdome; he had done, not only that which is <hi>unjuſt,</hi> but that which is <hi>impoſſible</hi> (as the Lawyers uſe to ſpeake) becauſe, <hi>eadem eſt impoſſibilitas Juris &amp; Naturae:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">F. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us.</note> That wich is impoſſible by <hi>Law,</hi> is as farre from being done, that is, <hi>Lawfully</hi> done; as that which is impoſſible, by <hi>Nature;</hi> For, ſtanding the <hi>condition</hi> of this promiſe, which is the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> of it, and ſtanding the <hi>circumſtances</hi> of Times, Perſons, Places, and ſuch like, which are <hi>ſubſervient</hi> unto it; The King <hi>could</hi> never <hi>doe</hi> it. And therefore in the third place, it is high time we ſhould looke, whether this Promiſe of <hi>not aboliſhing thoſe Lawes</hi> now to <hi>them,</hi> doe not bind, and tye up that other Promiſe to <hi>aboliſh</hi> them, which he ſince made unto my Lord of <hi>Ormond;</hi> as being <hi>impoſſible</hi> to be performed by him, without <hi>contradiction,</hi> and the breach of his former Promiſe; which is as <hi>impoſſible</hi> to <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, that the influence of this <hi>firſt</hi> promiſe, upon the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> promiſe is not ſuch; as renders that ſecond promiſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>impoſſible,</hi> or, which is as bad, <hi>unjuſt,</hi> it may be theſe two ſeverall waies demonſtrated. Firſt, by way of <hi>Annihilation</hi> and <hi>voiding</hi> of the firſt promiſe; and ſecondly, by <hi>Application</hi> of that firſt promiſe made in <hi>Generall,</hi> to ſuch ſeverall <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> which could never reaſonably be preſum'd to be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and contained, therein. Concerning the firſt of theſe: the <hi>Civilians</hi> tell us, that there are two waies how a man may<note place="margin">H. Grotius.</note> not keep his promiſe; and yet, not be <hi>unjuſt;</hi> The one is, by <hi>defect</hi> of a <hi>Condition,</hi> without which, the party promiſing contracts no <hi>obligation,</hi> and hither alſo, they referre that caſe; <hi>If the other party, firſt, doe not keep his word;</hi> For, the ſeverall branches of one and the ſame <hi>Contract,</hi> in the ſeverall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are but by the way of a <hi>Condition;</hi> as if it had been formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus expreſſed; <hi>This I promiſe to doe, if</hi> he <hi>will doe that.</hi> And ſo, this <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the Kings, that <hi>he never would conſent to the Abolition of the Lawes made in Ireland againſt Recuſants,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113157:24"/> it had no <hi>Condition</hi> at all, (and then the King contracts no <hi>obligation</hi> thereby; nor, is bound to keep it) or, it was made on this <hi>Condition,</hi> that His two Houſes, <hi>would firſt conſent, to this</hi> His preſent <hi>Expedition</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and put the Mannaging and Truſt of thoſe affaires, into His hands: In which <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they breaking firſt, on <hi>their</hi> parts, have left Him unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged on <hi>His.</hi> The other way is, by <hi>compenſation;</hi> and then, they tell us, that, that which we have promiſed, we may Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully not performe, and yet, not be reckoned <hi>unjuſt:</hi> when that which we promiſe, and <hi>performe not,</hi> is but of equall worth, if put into the Scales, with ſome other thing of Ours, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly is detained from us, and <hi>reſtor'd not.</hi> And ſo, if the King ſhould breake this <hi>one</hi> promiſe, which he made to them, yet were he not <hi>unjuſt;</hi> becauſe he would ſtill be behind hand with them, for thoſe <hi>iterated</hi> promiſes, and <hi>repeated</hi> Oathes, of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> of <hi>Subjection,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which they have <hi>made,</hi> and <hi>made</hi> againe, to <hi>Him,</hi> and yet have <hi>broke</hi> them All.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond way, to demonſtrate, that there is no <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> or <hi>Contradiction</hi> in theſe two promiſes; is, by <hi>Application</hi> of that firſt promiſe made in <hi>generall,</hi> to ſuch ſeverall <hi>particulars,</hi> which could never <hi>reaſonably</hi> be preſum'd, to be <hi>comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> and <hi>contained</hi> therein, when the promiſe was made. And to this purpoſe, obſerveable is that maxime in the Civill Law: <hi>Promiſſio Generalis non trahitur ad ea, ad quae veriſimiliter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. obligatione. ff. de pign. Capit.</note> 
                     <hi>ſi in ſpecie interrogatus fuiſſet, minime ſe obligaſſet,</hi> that is to ſay; No <hi>Generall</hi> promiſe, is to be drawne and extended unto thoſe things, to which, the party promiſing, in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, if He had been then queſtion'd in <hi>particular</hi> concerning them, would never have been <hi>obliged;</hi> and we apply it thus, The King, having a deſire to paſſe over into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to ſuppreſſe the Rebellion there, while it was young; and being willing alſo, to ſatisfy both His Houſes, that, in the purſuance thereof, He would uſe no diſhonourable and unworthy meanes, makes this ſolemne <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> that however the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells in <hi>Ireland</hi> might pretend, that they roſe only for <hi>Religion,</hi> and that, if they might be but permitted their <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113157:24"/> they would all be quiet; yet, He would <hi>never conſent,</hi> upon <hi>what pretence ſoever, to a Toleration of the Popiſh profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there;</hi> or, <hi>the Aboliſhing of the Lawes now in force againſt Popiſh Recuſants in that Kingdom.</hi> This is the <hi>Generall</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and to many <hi>particulars,</hi> it <hi>may be</hi> drawne and applyed: and to many; it <hi>may not.</hi> To thoſe onely particulars, ſaith the Law, <hi>may it</hi> be drawne; to which the King, if He had been interrogated <hi>particularly</hi> concerning them, would, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability have <hi>oblig'd</hi> himſelfe, when He made that <hi>Promiſe:</hi> as for example. When the King made this <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe, that He would <hi>never conſent to abrogate</hi> thoſe Lawes; If the Lords and Commons, had come to theſe <hi>particulars</hi> and ſaid; Your Majeſty promiſes <hi>never to Conſent</hi> to the Abolition of the Lawes againſt Recuſants, <hi>upon any pretence</hi> whatſoever; but, will you not <hi>conſent</hi> to <hi>aboliſh</hi> them, if you think, you have <hi>good Reaſon?</hi> Your Majeſty promiſes never to Conſent to it, while you are <hi>Here;</hi> But, will you remember to performe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, when you come <hi>There?</hi> Your Majeſty promiſes never to <hi>give Conſent,</hi> that is, to doe it, <hi>Willingly;</hi> But, will you not ſuffer your ſelfe, ſo to come within the Rebels power, that you muſt be forc't to doe, out of <hi>Neceſſity?</hi> To theſe <hi>particulars,</hi> and many more like theſe, becauſe it is very probable, the King would have <hi>oblig'd</hi> Himſelfe, (knowing the clean Intentions of His Heart) when He made this <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe, (ſaith the Law) reacheth thoſe <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</hi> and is <hi>applyable</hi> to <hi>them.</hi> But then, if the Lords and Commons, hearing this <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe of the Kings, that, upon <hi>no pretence</hi> whatſoever, He would <hi>aboliſh thoſe Lawes,</hi> had come to theſe <hi>particulars,</hi> and ſaid; Your Majeſty promiſes <hi>never to Conſent to an Abolition of thoſe Penall Lawes,</hi> becauſe, you are confident, we will aſſiſt you, in reducing thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels by <hi>Force,</hi> if <hi>Faire</hi> meanes, will not doe; But, if <hi>we</hi> ſhould <hi>Rebell</hi> againſt you, as well, as <hi>They;</hi> will you be <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> by this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> then? If we ſhould drive you to thoſe ſtreights, that, unleſſe the <hi>Catholiques</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> help you, the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Browniſts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> will diſpoyle you of your <hi>Revenues,</hi> and your <hi>Royalties:</hi> will take away your <hi>Lawes,</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:113157:25"/> nay, would take away your <hi>Life?</hi> will you be <hi>obliged,</hi> by this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> then? To theſe <hi>particulars,</hi> and others, like to theſe, becauſe it is more then probable, the King would never have <hi>oblig'd</hi> Himſelfe, being interrogated concerning them, when He made this <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe, of <hi>not Aboliſhing thoſe Lawes;</hi> Therefore, that <hi>generall</hi> Promiſe of His extends not, nor is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable, ſaith the Law, to theſe <hi>Particulars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo, by Conſequence, the King promiſing <hi>to Aboliſh thoſe Lawes,</hi> upon ſuch enforcements, and ſuch reaſons, as He would never have promiſed, <hi>Not to Aboliſh them;</hi> if He had been moved <hi>particularly</hi> thereunto; Does nothing by this <hi>ſecond,</hi> that either is <hi>unjuſt,</hi> or <hi>contradicts,</hi> that His <hi>firſt</hi> Promiſe. So that when the King made this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> the King did <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne</hi> is pleas'd to thinke, that He did not) <hi>that Declaration, wherein He doth declare, that He will not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Lawes made againſt Recuſants;</hi> but the King does <hi>not remember</hi> any thing in that <hi>Declaration,</hi> that tyes Him, why He may not <hi>make</hi> it; and, although many ſimple Citizens are men of ſo <hi>well-affected</hi> Ignorance, that they cannot ſee this; yet, I hope, there may be ſome, who may lye under the <hi>ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of having ſome <hi>common-Sence;</hi> and, I am ſure, They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but diſcerne it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The next are, the Queenes letters to the King; in them, you may ſee her unwearied endeavours by Sea and Land to raiſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces against the Parliament to deſtroy it. You ſee, She marcheth in the Head of an Army, and calls Her ſelfe the Generaliſſima. You may ſee farther in her letters, the great Intereſt She hath in the Kings Councells. No Office, or Place, can be diſpoſed of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her. You may ſee her letters, her advice concerning Peace. In making Peace, She adviſeth the King not to abandon thoſe that have ſerved Him, for feare they forſake Him in his need: She expreſſeth whom She meaneth; the Biſhops, and the poore Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. She adviſeth the King, for the honour of God, that He truſt not himſelfe in our hands. If He goe to</hi> London, <hi>before the Parliament is ended, She tells Him, He is undone. You may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113157:25"/> ſee, by her Letters, how active She is with the Duke of</hi> Lorraine, <hi>for ſending over 10000 men. You may ſee her Advice concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Parliament; She ſaith, That perpetuall Parliament muſt be disbanded; The reſt She ſaith, will follow: if the King conclude a Peace without that, She will into</hi> France, <hi>She ſaith. I am ſure, you cannot forget theſe paſſages.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>Having been ſomewhat over long in theſe <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> which paſt upon the Section going before: I am afrayd, I ſhall doe by theſe <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon this which is next unto it, as the Fellow did, by his Character and Diſcription of the <hi>great Church,</hi> which he reported to be <hi>two miles</hi> at leaſt in <hi>length,</hi> and when he perceived the company were not very forward to beleive it; he vowed, that notwithſtanding all that, it was not above <hi>two Inches</hi> in <hi>breadth,</hi> and ſo thought that he had well <hi>mended</hi> his <hi>Matter.</hi> For, all that I ſhall ſay, will be nothing but this: Here is much of <hi>Care,</hi> in a <hi>Pious</hi> and moſt <hi>Exemplary</hi> Queene; here is nothing of <hi>Crime;</hi> And He that will thinke the worſe of <hi>Good Councell,</hi> becauſe his <hi>Wife</hi> does give it; Let ſome other man think <hi>better</hi> of his <hi>Wife</hi> then He <hi>does:</hi> and let Him not <hi>beleeve</hi> it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the King's Letters to the Queene, you may obſerve theſe following particulars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt His Apology to Her, for calling us a Parliament, at the laſt Treaty. It ſeemes ſhe was offended at it, and you may ſee by his letters, with what difficulty he did it; For he ſaith,</hi> that if but two more had joyned with him in opinion to the contrary, he would never have done it, <hi>yet he hath told us;</hi> He will keep all the Acts of this Parliament inviolable. <hi>How thoſe can ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, let all men Judge. He hath told us,</hi> that he will maintaine the Lawes, and obſerve them himſelfe; <hi>yet you may ſee, he layes that bloud of the Kingdom which is ſhed in theſe Warres upon the ſhedding of the</hi> Innocent <hi>bloud, as he calls it,</hi> of my Lord
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113157:26"/> Strafford. <hi>Yet my Lord of</hi> Strafford <hi>was condemned by himſelfe, and by the Law, that he ſaith he will maintaine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>The King is here charg'd with a <hi>brace</hi> of Contradictions; May he never receive more hurt from any other <hi>Bullet.</hi> The firſt is, that <hi>he makes an Apology</hi> to the Queene for calling the Rebels at Weſtminſter, <hi>a Parliament;</hi> and yet he profeſſes, he will <hi>keep inviolable all the Acts of this Parliament;</hi> This is <hi>one</hi> horrible Contradiction, and all men are called in to Iudge, how theſe two can <hi>ſtand together.</hi> The ſecond is, That the King tells them He will <hi>maintaine the Lawes and obſerve them,</hi> and yet he calls the bloud of my Lord <hi>Strafford, [the innocent bloud of my Lord Strafford</hi>] which was ſhed by the <hi>Law,</hi> which he ſaith, <hi>he will maintaine;</hi> This is another. For the firſt of theſe: The King may <hi>keep inviolable</hi> all <hi>Acts</hi> that have bin made this Parliament; that is, all <hi>Acts</hi> which have paſſed <hi>Both Houſes,</hi> and had his <hi>owne Conſent,</hi> while He was joyned <hi>with</hi> them; For then they were a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and a perfect Body: and yet the King, may not account that excrementitious Part of that Body, which now remaines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to be a <hi>Parliament;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>poſſeſſe the place</hi> of the Parliament, no more then a man ſworne a <hi>Squire</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> to ſome Prince, and doing the <hi>Perſon</hi> of that Prince all <hi>Service,</hi> can thinke himſelfe bound to give <hi>Reverence</hi> to his <hi>Cloſe-ſtoole,</hi> if it ſhould, by chance, be brought and ſet downe, in the <hi>Preſence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then, for that other charge, about my Lord of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> Firſt, what a ſimple Inference is this: The King thinks my Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi> dyed Innocent, who was condemned by <hi>Law;</hi> Therefore the King does <hi>not maintaine the Law?</hi> Certainly, many poore men, in a yeare, through the <hi>malice</hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> through the <hi>preſumptions,</hi> or <hi>perjuries,</hi> of thoſe that bring in <hi>Evidence</hi> againſt them, <hi>have</hi> bin, and <hi>may</hi> be thought <hi>Innocently</hi> condemn'd, as guilty perſons of that fact, which they never did, and yet thoſe men that thinke ſo, <hi>may</hi> not, nay <hi>doe</hi> not, thinke the Law <hi>nocent,</hi> which condemnes them, or hold it no longer fitting for to be <hi>maintayned.</hi> In the ſecond place,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113157:26"/> what ever that <hi>Law</hi> was, whereby my Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi> was condemned, all the world knowes, they themſelves have taken order, that the proceeding againſt my Lord of <hi>Strafford,</hi> by that <hi>Law,</hi> ſhould not be drawne to Preſident for after times: And yet theſe men charge the King for not <hi>maintayning that Law,</hi> which they themſelves are <hi>aſhamed</hi> of, and will not <hi>ſtand by.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſee, how preſſing He is to the Queene, to procure ayde from the Duke of</hi> Lorraine: <hi>upon hopes of his comming He is very glad, and ſaith;</hi> the Prince of Orange ſhall help to tranſport His Souldiers. <hi>Compare this with his former Declarations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Forreigne Forces. It needs no Aggravation. We have all of us, more Cauſe to pray for Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For his maintaining the Lawes, you may obſerve in a Letter dated in</hi> March <hi>laſt, to the Queene, there is this paſſage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I give Thee leave to promiſe in my Name, to all that thou thinkeſt fit, that I will take away all the Penall Lawes againſt the Roman Catholiques in <hi>England,</hi> as ſoone, as God ſhall enable me to doe it, ſo as I may by their meanes have ſuch aſſiſtance, as may deſerve ſo great a favour, and enable me to doe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this promiſe of His, He enjoynes much ſecrecy, which He hath need to doe, being ſo contrary to former Declarations, and Protestations. If this be done, He may as well alter and take away all our Lawes, both for property and liberty. Theſe Lawes againſt Papiſts, are of as much force, and bind as much as any Lawes whatſoever. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon all theſe Letters and Paſſages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you may obſerve the great Deſigne to put an end to this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, although it cannot be done without the Conſent of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, and the Kings joyning with them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſee another Deſigne is, to take away all Lawes againſt Recuſants, and that muſt be, when the King is able to doe it, as He ſaith, and that cannot be, without Force. You ſee, to enable himſelfe to doe theſe things, He invites in Forreigne Forces:</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113157:27"/> 
                     <hi>You ſee He deales with Papiſts and Proteſtants, and all to aſſiſt Him, againſt the Parliament. You ſee by thoſe letters, what Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Immunities are promiſed to Papiſts, and nothing at all to His Proteſtant Subjects; You ſee, the great Truſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth in the Queene, to make a bargaine for Him; although it concerne Religion, which is the ſtrongeſt poynt of Confidence, He can expreſſe to her. I need not repeat the words.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Animadverſions.</head>
                  <p>All this upon the matter, is nothing but ſome of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſles</hi> cold <hi>meate,</hi> newly <hi>minc't:</hi> and the whole <hi>face</hi> of this part of the diſcourſe, is but dreſt up, like M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sheriffes <hi>dore;</hi> ſomewhat perchance added of <hi>Paint,</hi> but, ſtill the ſame <hi>Poſt.</hi> All that hath <hi>not</hi> been <hi>ſaid</hi> and <hi>anſwer'd</hi> before, is this; That the King <hi>repoſeth ſuch truſt in the Queene,</hi> as to <hi>make a Bargaine</hi> for him, though it concerne <hi>Religion;</hi> which is the <hi>ſtrongeſt poynt of confidence He can expreſſe unto Her.</hi> And to this M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Browne,</hi> in a negligent and looſe manner, addes, <hi>I need not repeat his wordes.</hi> But, is the matter worth the <hi>ſeeing,</hi> and are the words not worth the <hi>ſaying?</hi> pray let us heare you <hi>repeate</hi> them. Your Citizens are uſed to <hi>repetitions;</hi> and will like it well enough, unleſſe, you think to put them off (as they doe Beggars) with ſaying, <hi>It was the laſt thing you did;</hi> for I am ſure, in all this Section, you have done nothing elſe, but <hi>repeated,</hi> what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Liſle</hi> hath ſaid before you. Well, if you will not <hi>repeat</hi> them, I will <hi>repeat</hi> them for you. For, I will not have my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>London,</hi> couſened in their <hi>meaſure.</hi> You ſhall not think, to <hi>ſerve</hi> them, with a bare <hi>yard,</hi> and then, <hi>ſave</hi> the <hi>thumb.</hi> The whole period of the Kings Letter, is this: <hi>I need not tell thee what ſecrecy this buſineſſe requires; yet this I will ſay, that this is the greateſt poynt of confidence I can expreſſe to thee; For, it is no thankes to me, to truſt thee in any thing elſe, but in this, which is the</hi> only thing of difference in opinion <hi>betwixt us.</hi> And can a cleerer teſtimony be given, of the Kings <hi>uprightneſſe</hi> in the poynt of His <hi>Religion?</hi> If men would not <hi>tread inward</hi> with their faith, and believe nothing but what makes for their own <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>advantages,</hi> the <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Innocence,</hi> could
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113157:27"/> not invent a clearer <hi>Light</hi> to ſhine by. For, here is <hi>Fire</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Smoake:</hi> here is <hi>Truth,</hi> without <hi>modifications</hi> and <hi>diſguiſes.</hi> Here is nothing of <hi>deſigne,</hi> like that profeſſion the King makes in His often <hi>Declarations,</hi> (which the jealous world is tender of believing, for feare of being <hi>couſened</hi>) but here is a <hi>downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> profeſſion, of <hi>differing in Religion</hi> with Her, who, with all Her heart (I dare ſay) could wiſh, the King would have <hi>deceived</hi> Her. And therefore, as ſome Heretiques, are ſaid to worſhip <hi>Judas,</hi> not becauſe he <hi>betray'd</hi> his Lord and Maſter, but, becauſe of that ineſtimable <hi>benefit</hi> which accrewed to mankind by meanes of his <hi>betraying,</hi> which otherwiſe could never have befallen it: So, will ſome men, who doubted here to fore, of the Kings <hi>Innocence</hi> in His <hi>publick Declarations,</hi> have reaſon to forgive this <hi>Rape</hi> upon His <hi>private Letters,</hi> for the very Religion of this <hi>Evidence</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, could never have ſo clearely been tranſmitted, and derived unto them.</p>
                  <p>And thus, have you ſeen the bottome of that <hi>Heart,</hi> which the Scripture calls <hi>unſearcheable.</hi> The <hi>Cabinet</hi> hath imparted<note place="margin">Prov. 25. 2.</note> to you, ſo perfect an <hi>Image</hi> of the Kings very <hi>Thoughts;</hi> that the <hi>Rack</hi> could not afford a clearer. The Rebells have often promiſed to make him a <hi>Great King;</hi> and now, (as the High Prieſt, when he prophecyed) they have <hi>made</hi> him ſo indeed, when they never <hi>meant</hi> it; In ſtead of His <hi>Three Kingdomes,</hi> they have endowed him with <hi>Foure</hi> ſeverall <hi>Empires;</hi> For ſo long as <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo long as <hi>Husbands</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> ſhall live upon this habitable earth; they will all ſubmit to the <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>His</hi> Pen, and confeſſe themſelves <hi>ſubdued,</hi> in their chiefeſt <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Glories.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a <hi>Man,</hi> ſee, but with what <hi>Sagacity</hi> He writes, and with what <hi>Judgement;</hi> See, but what a <hi>cleane ſence</hi> he hath of <hi>things;</hi> which does ſo overlooke all his moſt perplexed <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires,</hi> that they ſeem to <hi>bluſh,</hi> they have no better <hi>Difficulties.</hi> See, but how farre his <hi>Wiſdome</hi> lookes into mens <hi>Perſons;</hi> which doth ſo weigh <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>Actions,</hi> with the <hi>graines</hi> and <hi>allowance</hi> of their unworthy, ſervile <hi>ends;</hi> that He ſeems not more to <hi>obſerve,</hi> then <hi>Prophecy.</hi> See, but what an even
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113157:28"/> 
                     <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Elegancy</hi> runnes through every line; which beares and leaps, as much, in the deſcription of His <hi>ſaddeſt</hi> condition, as of his <hi>ſereneſt</hi> Fortune; in ſo much, that, poſterity will a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, <hi>love</hi> His <hi>Miſery,</hi> for her very <hi>clothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then, as a <hi>Husband,</hi> doe but obſerve, how <hi>kinde</hi> He is, and yet withall, how <hi>Chaſt?</hi> How full of <hi>warme</hi> expreſſions of Love, and yet how farre from <hi>Wanton?</hi> Doe but obſerve, how He weighes his <hi>own</hi> Health, by His Wives <hi>Standard;</hi> Every line beares a <hi>Venus</hi> in it, and yet, bears no <hi>Doves;</hi> And He drives the <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Thoughts,</hi> between the Queen and Him, with ſo much <hi>eagerneſſe,</hi> and yet, with ſo much <hi>Innocence</hi> in all His Letters, as if He <hi>meant,</hi> they ſhould be <hi>intercepted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſee, but what a <hi>Conſcience</hi> He makes of <hi>Oathes;</hi> eſteeming them, not (according to the Popular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) as if their <hi>Ceremonie,</hi> made them the leſſe <hi>Sacred.</hi> Or, as too many men uſe them in the World, as <hi>bracelets</hi> to their <hi>Speech,</hi> not (as they are indeed) as <hi>chaines</hi> unto their <hi>Soule;</hi> look but how He <hi>ſtartles</hi> at the name of <hi>Sacriledge;</hi> though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo <hi>commodious</hi> a ſinne; Doe but obſerve, notwithſtanding all his <hi>ſuccours</hi> from the Queene, on whom His patient eyes doe wait for better <hi>Helpe;</hi> how he throwes himſelfe upon the <hi>Providence</hi> of God; how he <hi>rolles,</hi> and <hi>gathers</hi> upon his <hi>juſtice,</hi> in a confidence, that, as their <hi>mutuall intereſt</hi> in <hi>innocent Blood,</hi> hath hither to poys'd the <hi>ballance,</hi> between <hi>both ſides:</hi> So now, the Rebells overflowing <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> will at laſt, turne the <hi>Scales.</hi> And then, doe but obſerve His <hi>Conſtancy</hi> to the Proteſtant <hi>Religion;</hi> which is the <hi>greateſt difference,</hi> between His <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>Him;</hi> and yet ſuch a difference too, that <hi>diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa virtus parem laudem conſecuta eſt,</hi> (as the Orator ſpeaks of <hi>Thucydides</hi> and <hi>Herodotus</hi> in his Inſtitutions;) He is as much to be admired, for his <hi>Difference,</hi> as for his <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, as a <hi>King,</hi> ſee, but what a <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>True</hi> ſoule He bears to <hi>Iuſtice;</hi> which none of His ſad <hi>infelicities,</hi> can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. A Soule, that would come off <hi>True,</hi> were it put to <hi>Plato's</hi> tryall; who ſaies, that, <hi>for a man to approve himſelfe a</hi> True Iuſt<note place="margin">Plato.</note> 
                     <hi>man</hi> indeed; <hi>His</hi> vertue <hi>muſt be</hi> ſpoyl'd <hi>of all her</hi> ornaments; <hi>He muſt be thought a</hi> vitious <hi>man, though, he be never ſo</hi> virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113157:28"/> 
                     <hi>He muſt be reekon'd a</hi> Falſe <hi>man of his word, though he be never ſo</hi> True; <hi>He muſt be</hi> mockt, ſcorn'd, <hi>and</hi> derided, <hi>as though he were a</hi> Foole, <hi>be he never ſo</hi> Wiſe; <hi>nay ſaith that</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher (<hi>I had almoſt ſaid, that</hi> Father) <hi>He muſt give up his</hi> Life, <hi>into the power of thoſe that ſeek it,</hi> laetius eſſe honeſtum putans, quoties magno ſibi conſtat; <hi>eſteeming it the</hi> greateſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>of Honeſty, to be gotten at the</hi> deareſt purchaſe. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe <hi>Tryalls</hi> hath the King endur'd, and yet, hath never ſhrinkt? How hath his happy <hi>Government</hi> been traduced, and his own ſacred <hi>Perſon,</hi> expoſed? How hath his <hi>Affection</hi> been <hi>abuſed,</hi> and his <hi>Iudgement</hi> ſcorn'd? how often hath he been reputed for a <hi>weake</hi> man? nay, how often for a <hi>Wicked?</hi> how often hath he been eſteemed a <hi>Fickle</hi> man, nay, how oft a <hi>Falſe?</hi> and yet, our of all theſe His <hi>Letters,</hi> (which are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Thoughts</hi> of the Kings <hi>heart,</hi> but <hi>once remoov'd;</hi> and, where all the <hi>ſcapes</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Breeding,</hi> were moſt like to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:) cannot their acute malice, impute or faſten, any one thing upon him, which is inconſiſtent, either with the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Prudence, Juſtice, Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Honour.</hi> Inſomuch, that, notwithſtanding it be very probable, that the <hi>Publication</hi> of theſe <hi>Papers,</hi> is conceived by ſome ſlight men at this preſent, as an <hi>atteſtation</hi> of the <hi>perfect glories</hi> of their <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> and to ſhew the world, how <hi>neare they came,</hi> even to the very <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of the King: yet, it is altogether as probable, that, to men of the next <hi>ſad,</hi> and <hi>wiſer</hi> age, this very <hi>Triumph,</hi> will confute the <hi>Victory;</hi> whileſt, attributing that juſt veneration, which is due from all <hi>cleane</hi> eyes, to the <hi>Magistery</hi> of that <hi>Religion, Elegancy, Judgement, Wit,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> which ruleth in this <hi>haſty</hi> compoſition and <hi>ſodaine</hi> ſtile; They will never gaine this <hi>Power</hi> over their <hi>beliefe,</hi> or ſo farre <hi>ſubdue</hi> their <hi>underſtanding,</hi> as to think, either that ſo <hi>decryed</hi> a King, as He hath been, could <hi>Penne</hi> ſuch Papers, or, that ſuch <hi>wiſe</hi> Rebells, as they would faine be thought, could <hi>Print</hi> them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
